hi everyone so I've wanted to make this
video for a while it is a comprehensive
but General audience introduction to
large language models like Chachi PT and
what I'm hoping to achieve in this video
is to give you kind of mental models for
thinking through what it is that this
tool is it is obviously magical and
amazing in some respects it's uh really
good at some things not very good at
other things and there's also a lot of
sharp edges to be aware of so what is
behind this text box you can put
anything in there and press enter but uh
what should we be putting there and what
are these words generated back how does
this work and what what are you talking
to exactly so I'm hoping to get at all
those topics in this video we're going
to go through the entire pipeline of how
this stuff is built but I'm going to
keep everything uh sort of accessible to
a general audience so let's take a look
at first how you build something like
chpt and along the way I'm going to talk
about um you know some of the sort of
cognitive psychological implications of
the tools okay so let's build Chachi PT
so there's going to be multiple stages
arranged sequentially the first stage is
called the pre-training stage and the
first step of the pre-training stage is
to download and process the internet now
to get a sense of what this roughly
looks like I recommend looking at this
URL here so um this company called
hugging face uh collected and created
and curated this data set called Fine
web and they go into a lot of detail on
this block post on how how they
constructed the fine web data set and
all of the major llm providers like open
AI anthropic and Google and so on will
have some equivalent internally of
something like the fine web data set so
roughly what are we trying to achieve
here we're trying to get ton of text
from the internet from publicly
available sources so we're trying to
have a huge quantity of very high
quality documents and we also want very
large diversity of documents because we
want to have a lot of knowledge inside
these models so we want large diversity
of high quality documents and we want
many many of them and achieving this is
uh quite complicated and as you can see
here takes multiple stages to do well so
let's take a look at what some of these
stages look like in a bit for now I'd
like to just like to note that for
example the fine web data set which is
fairly representative what you would see
in a production grade application
actually ends up being only about 44
terabyt of dis space um you can get a
USB stick for like a terabyte very
easily or I think this could fit on a
single hard drive almost today so this
is not a huge amount of data at the end
of the day even though the internet is
very very large we're working with text
and we're also filtering it aggressively
so we end up with about 44 terabytes in
this example so let's take a look at uh
kind of what this data looks like and
what some of these stages uh also are so
the starting point for a lot of these
efforts and something that contributes
most of the data by the end of it is
Data from common crawl so common craw is
an organization that has been basically
scouring the internet since 2007 so as
of 2024 for example common CW has
indexed 2.7 billion web
pages uh and uh they have all these
crawlers going around the internet and
what you end up doing basically is you
start with a few seed web pages and then
you follow all the links and you just
keep following links and you keep
indexing all the information and you end
up with a ton of data of the internet
over time so this is usually the
starting point for a lot of the uh for a
lot of these efforts now this common C
data is quite raw and is filtered in
many many different ways
so here they Pro they document this is
the same diagram they document a little
bit the kind of processing that happens
in these stages so the first thing here
is something called URL
filtering so what that is referring to
is that there's these block
lists of uh basically URLs that are or
domains that uh you don't want to be
getting data from so usually this
includes things like U malware websites
spam websites marketing websites uh
racist websites adult sites and things
like that so there's a ton of different
types of websites that are just
eliminated at this stage because we
don't want them in our data set um the
second part is text extraction you have
to remember that all these web pages
this is the raw HTML of these web pages
that are being saved by these crawlers
so when I go to inspect
here this is what the raw HTML actually
looks like you'll notice that it's got
all this markup uh like lists and stuff
like that and there's CSS and all this
kind of stuff so this is um computer
code almost for these web pages but what
we really want is we just want this text
right we just want the text of this web
page and we don't want the navigation
and things like that so there's a lot of
filtering and processing uh and heris
that go into uh adequately filtering for
just their uh good content of these web
pages the next stage here is language
filtering so for example fine web
filters uh using a language classifier
they try to guess what language every
single web page is in and then they only
keep web pages that have more than 65%
of English as an
example and so you can get a sense that
this is like a design decision that
different companies can uh can uh take
for themselves what fraction of all
different types of languages are we
going to include in our data set because
for example if we filter out all of the
Spanish as an example then you might
imagine that our model later will not be
very good at Spanish because it's just
never seen that much data of that
language and so different companies can
focus on multilingual performance to uh
to a different degree as an example so
fine web is quite focused on English and
so their language model if they end up
training one later will be very good at
English but not may be very good at
other
languages after language filtering
there's a few other filtering steps and
D duplication and things like that um
finishing with for example the pii
removal this is personally identifiable
information so as an example addresses
Social Security numbers and things like
that you would try to detect them and
you would try to filter out those kinds
of web pages from the the data set as
well so there's a lot of stages here and
I won't go into full detail but it is a
fairly extensive part of the
pre-processing and you end up with for
example the fine web data set so when
you click in on it uh you can see some
examples here of what this actually ends
up looking like and anyone can download
this on the huging phase web page and so
here are some examples of the final text
that ends up in the training set so this
is some article about tornadoes in
2012 um so there's some t tadoes in 2020
in 2012 and what
happened uh this next one is something
about did you know you have two little
yellow 9vt battery sized adrenal glands
in your body okay so this is some kind
of a odd medical
article so just think of these as
basically uh web pages on the internet
filtered just for the text in various
ways and now we have a ton of text 40
terabytes off it and that now is the
starting point for the next step of this
stage now I wanted to give you an
intuitive sense of where we are right
now so I took the first 200 web pages
here and remember we have tons of them
and I just take all that text and I just
put it all together concatenate it and
so this is what we end up with we just
get this just just raw text raw internet
text and there's a ton of it even in
these 200 web pages so I can continue
zooming out here and we just have this
like massive tapestry of Text data and
this text data has all these p patterns
and what we want to do now is we want to
start training neural networks on this
data so the neural networks can
internalize and model how this text
flows right so we just have this giant
texture of text and now we want to get
neural Nets that mimic it okay now
before we plug text into neural networks
we have to decide how we're going to
represent this text uh and how we're
going to feed it in now the way our
technology works for these neuron Lots
is that they expect
a one-dimensional sequence of symbols
and they want a finite set of symbols
that are possible and so we have to
decide what are the symbols and then we
have to represent our data as
one-dimensional sequence of those
symbols so right now what we have is a
onedimensional sequence of text it
starts here and it goes here and then it
comes here Etc so this is a
onedimensional sequence even though on
my monitor of course it's laid out in a
two-dimensional way but it goes from
left to right and top to bottom right so
it's a one-dimensional sequence of text
now this being computers of course
there's an underlying representation
here so if I do what's called utf8 uh
encode this text then I can get the raw
bits that correspond to this text in the
computer and that's what uh that looks
like this so it turns out that for
example this very first bar here is the
first uh eight bits as an
example so what is this thing right this
is um representation that we are looking
for uh in in a certain sense we have
exactly two possible symbols zero and
one and we have a very long sequence of
it right now as it turns out um this
sequence length is actually going to be
very finite and precious resource uh in
our neural network and we actually don't
want extremely long sequences of just
two symbols instead what we want is we
want to trade off uh this um symbol
size uh of this vocabulary as we call it
and the resulting sequence length so we
don't want just two symbols and
extremely long sequences we're going to
want more symbols and shorter sequences
okay so one naive way of compressing or
decreasing the length of our sequence
here is to basically uh consider some
group of consecutive bits for example
eight bits and group them into a single
what's called bite so because uh these
bits are either on or off if we take a
group of eight of them there turns out
to be only 256 possible combinations of
how these bits could be on or off and so
therefore we can re repesent this
sequence into a sequence of bytes
instead so this sequence of bytes will
be eight times shorter but now we have
256 possible symbols so every number
here goes from 0 to
255 now I really encourage you to think
of these not as numbers but as unique
IDs or like unique symbols so maybe it's
a bit more maybe it's better to actually
think of these to replace every one of
these with a unique Emoji you'd get
something like this so um we basically
have a sequence of emojis and there's
256 possible emojis you can think of it
that way now it turns out that in
production for state-of-the-art language
models uh you actually want to go even
Beyond this you want to continue to
shrink the length of the sequence uh
because again it is a precious resource
in return for more symbols in your
vocabulary and the way this is done is
done by running what's called The Bite
pair encoding algorithm and the way this
works is we're basically looking for
consecutive bytes or symbols that are
very common so for example turns out
that the sequence 116 followed by 32 is
quite common and occurs very frequently
so what we're going to do is we're going
to group uh this um pair into a new
symbol so we're going to Mint a symbol
with an ID 256 and we're going to
rewrite every single uh pair 11632 with
this new symbol and then can we can
iterate this algorithm as many times as
we wish and each time when we mint a new
symbol we're decreasing the length and
we're increasing the symbol size and in
practice it turns out that a pretty good
setting of um the basically the
vocabulary size turns out to be about
100,000 possible symbols so in
particular GPT 4 uses
100,
277 symbols
um and this process of converting from
raw text into these symbols or as we
call them tokens is the process called
tokenization so let's now take a look at
how gp4 performs tokenization conting
from text to tokens and from tokens back
to text and what this actually looks
like so one website I like to use to
explore these token representations is
called tick tokenizer and so come here
to the drop down and select CL 100 a
base which is the gp4 base model
tokenizer and here on the left you can
put in text and it shows you the
tokenization of that text so for example
heo space
world so hello world turns out to be
exactly two Tokens The Token hello which
is the token with ID
15339 and the token space
world that is the token 1
1917 so um hello space world now if I
was to join these two for example I'm
going to get again two tokens but it's
the token H followed by the token L
world without the
H um if I put in two Spa two spaces here
between hello and world it's again a
different uh tokenization there's a new
token 220
here okay so you can play with this and
see what happens here also keep in mind
this is not uh this is case sensitive so
if this is a capital H it is something
else or if it's uh hello world then
actually this ends up being three tokens
instead of just two
tokens yeah so you can play with this
and get an sort of like an intuitive
sense of uh what these tokens work like
we're actually going to loop around to
tokenization a bit later in the video
for now I just wanted to show you the
website and I wanted to uh show you that
this text basically at the end of the
day so for example if I take one line
here this is what GT4 will see it as so
this text will be a sequence of length
62 this is the sequence here and this is
how the chunks of text correspond to
these symbols and again there's 100,
27777 possible symbols and we now have
one-dimensional sequences of those
symbols so um yeah we're going to come
back to tokenization but that's uh for
now where we are okay so what I've done
now is I've taken this uh sequence of
text that we have here in the data set
and I have re-represented it using our
tokenizer into a sequence of tokens and
this is what that looks like now so for
example when we go back to the Fine web
data set they mentioned that not only is
this 44 terab of dis space but this is
about a 15 trillion token sequence of um
in this data set and so here these are
just some of the first uh one or two or
three or a few thousand here I think uh
tokens of this data set but there's 15
trillion here uh to keep in mind and
again keep in mind one more time that
all of these represent little text
chunks they're all just like atoms of
these sequences and the numbers here
don't make any sense they're just uh
they're just unique IDs okay so now we
get to the fun part which is the uh
neural network training and this is
where a lot of the heavy lifting happens
computationally when you're training
these neural networks so what we do here
in this this step is we want to model
the statistical relationships of how
these tokens follow each other in the
sequence so what we do is we come into
the data and we take Windows of tokens
so we take a window of tokens uh from
this data fairly
randomly and um the windows length can
range anywhere anywhere between uh zero
tokens actually all the way up to some
maximum size that we decide on uh so for
example in practice you could see a
token with Windows of say 8,000 tokens
now in principle we can use arbitrary
window lengths of tokens uh but uh
processing very long uh basically U
window sequences would just be very
computationally expensive so we just
kind of decide that say 8,000 is a good
number or 4,000 or 16,000 and we crop it
there now in this example I'm going to
be uh taking the first four tokens just
so everything fits nicely so these
tokens
we're going to take a window of four
tokens this bar view in and space single
which are these token
IDs and now what we're trying to do here
is we're trying to basically predict the
token that comes next in the sequence so
3962 comes next right so what we do now
here is that we call this the context
these four tokens are context and they
feed into a neural
network and this is the input to the
neural network
now I'm going to go into the detail of
what's inside this neural network in a
little bit for now it's important to
understand is the input and the output
of the neural net so the input are
sequences of tokens of variable length
anywhere between zero and some maximum
size like 8,000 the output now is a
prediction for what comes next so
because our vocabulary has
100277 possible tokens the neural
network is going to Output exactly that
many numbers
and all of those numbers correspond to
the probability of that token as coming
next in the sequence so it's making
guesses about what comes
next um in the beginning this neural
network is randomly initialized so um
and we're going to see in a little bit
what that means but it's a it's a it's a
random transformation so these
probabilities in the very beginning of
the training are also going to be kind
of random uh so here I have three
examples but keep in mind that there's
100,000 numbers here um so the
probability of this token space
Direction neural network is saying that
this is 4% likely right now 11799 is 2%
and then here the probility of 3962
which is post is 3% now of course we've
sampled this window from our data set so
we know what comes next we know and
that's the label we know that the
correct answer is that 3962 actually
comes next in the sequence so now what
we have is this mathematical process for
doing an update to the neural network we
have the way of tuning it and uh we're
going to go into a little bit of of
detail in a bit but basically we know
that this probability here of 3% we want
this probability to be higher and we
want the probabilities of all the other
tokens to be
lower and so we have a way of
mathematically calculating how to adjust
and update the neural network so that
the correct answer has a slightly higher
probability so if I do an update to the
neural network now the next time I Fe
this particular sequence of four tokens
into neural network the neural network
will be slightly adjusted now and it
will say Okay post is maybe 4% and case
now maybe is
1% and uh Direction could become 2% or
something like that and so we have a way
of nudging of slightly updating the
neuronet to um basically give a higher
probability to the correct token that
comes next in the sequence and now you
just have to remember that this process
happens not just for uh this um token
here where these four fed in and
predicted this one this process happens
at the same time for all of these tokens
in the entire data set and so in
practice we sample little windows little
batches of Windows and then at every
single one of these tokens we want to
adjust our neural network so that the
probability of that token becomes
slightly higher and this all happens in
parallel in large batches of these
tokens and this is the process of
training the neural network it's a
sequence of updating it so that it's
predictions match up the statistics of
what actually happens in your training
set and its probabilities become
consistent with the uh statistical
patterns of how these tokens follow each
other in the data so let's now briefly
get into the internals of these neural
networks just to give you a sense of
what's inside so neural network
internals so as I mentioned we have
these inputs uh that are sequences of
tokens in this case this is four input
tokens but this can be anywhere between
zero up to let's say 8,000 tokens in
principle this can be an infinite number
of tokens we just uh it would just be
too computationally expensive to process
an infinite number of tokens so we just
crop it at a certain length and that
becomes the maximum context length of
that uh
model now these inputs X are mixed up in
a giant mathematical expression together
with the parameters or the weights of
these neural networks so here I'm
showing six example parameters and their
setting but in practice these uh um
modern neural networks will have
billions of these uh parameters and in
the beginning these parameters are
completely randomly set now with a
random setting of parameters you might
expect that this uh this neural network
would make random predictions and it
does in the beginning it's totally
random predictions but it's through this
process of iteratively updating the
network uh as and we call that process
training a neural network so uh that the
setting of these parameters gets
adjusted such that the outputs of our
neural network becomes consistent with
the patterns seen in our training
set so think of these parameters as kind
of like knobs on a DJ set and as you're
twiddling these knobs you're getting
different uh predictions for every
possible uh token sequence input and
training in neural network just means
discovering a setting of parameters that
seems to be consistent with the
statistics of the training
set now let me just give you an example
what this giant mathematical expression
looks like just to give you a sense and
modern networks are massive expressions
with trillions of terms probably but let
me just show you a simple example here
it would look something like this I mean
these are the kinds of Expressions just
to show you that it's not very scary we
have inputs x uh like X1 x2 in this case
two example inputs and they get mixed up
with the weights of the network w0 W1 2
3 Etc and this mixing is simple things
like multiplication addition addition
exponentiation division Etc and it is
the subject of neural network
architecture research to design
effective mathematical Expressions uh
that have a lot of uh kind of convenient
characteristics they are expressive
they're optimizable they're paralyzable
Etc and so but uh at the end of the day
these are these are not complex
expressions and basically they mix up
the inputs with the parameters to make
predictions and we're optimizing uh the
parameters of this neural network so
that the predictions come out consistent
with the training set now I would like
to show you an actual production grade
example of what these neural networks
look like so for that I encourage you to
go to this website that has a very nice
visualization of one of these
networks so this is what you will find
on this website and this neural network
here that is used in production settings
has this special kind of structure this
network is called the Transformer and
this particular one as an example has 8
5,000 roughly
parameters now here on the top we take
the inputs which are the token
sequences and then information flows
through the neural network until the
output which here are the logit softmax
but these are the predictions for what
comes next what token comes
next and then here there's a sequence of
Transformations and all these
intermediate values that get produced
inside this mathematical expression s it
is sort of predicting what comes next so
as an example these tokens are embedded
into kind of like this distributed
representation as it's called so every
possible token has kind of like a vector
that represents it inside the neural
network so first we embed the tokens and
then those values uh kind of like flow
through this diagram and these are all
very simple mathematical Expressions
individually so we have layer norms and
Matrix multiplications and uh soft Maxes
and so on so here kind of like the
attention block of this Transformer and
then information kind of flows through
into the multi-layer perceptron block
and so on and all these numbers here
these are the intermediate values of the
expression and uh you can almost think
of these as kind of like the firing
rates of these synthetic neurons but I
would caution you to uh not um kind of
think of it too much like neurons
because these are extremely simple
neurons compared to the neurons you
would find in your brain your biological
neurons are very complex dynamical
processes that have memory and so on
there's no memory in this expression
it's a fixed mathematical expression
from input to Output with no memory it's
just a
stateless so these are very simple
neurons in comparison to biological
neurons but you can still kind of
loosely think of this as like a
synthetic piece of uh brain tissue if
you if you like uh to think about it
that way so information flows through
all these neurons fire until we get to
the predictions now I'm not actually
going to dwell too much on the precise
kind of like mathematical details of all
these Transformations honestly I don't
think it's that important to get into
what's really important to understand is
that this is a mathematical function it
is uh parameterized by some fixed set of
parameters like say 85,000 of them and
it is a way of transforming inputs into
outputs and as we twiddle the parameters
we are getting uh different kinds of
predictions and then we need to find a
good setting of these parameters so that
the predictions uh sort of match up with
the patterns seen in training set
so that's the Transformer okay so I've
shown you the internals of the neural
network and we talked a bit about the
process of training it I want to cover
one more major stage of working with
these networks and that is the stage
called inference so in inference what
we're doing is we're generating new data
from the model and so uh we want to
basically see what kind of patterns it
has internalized in the parameters of
its Network so to generate from the
model is relatively straightforward
we start with some tokens that are
basically your prefix like what you want
to start with so say we want to start
with the token 91 well we feed it into
the
network and remember that the network
gives us probabilities right it gives us
this probability Vector here so what we
can do now is we can basically flip a
biased coin so um we can sample uh
basically a token based on this
probability distribution so the tokens
that are given High probability by the
model are more likely to be sampled when
you flip this biased coin you can think
of it that way so we sample from the
distribution to get a single unique
token so for example token 860 comes
next uh so 860 in this case when we're
generating from model could come next
now 860 is a relatively likely token it
might not be the only possible token in
this case there could be many other
tokens that could have been sampled but
we could see that 86c is a relatively
likely token as an example and indeed in
our training examp example here 860 does
follow 91 so let's now say that we um
continue the process so after 91 there's
a60 we append it and we again ask what
is the third token let's sample and
let's just say that it's 287 exactly as
here let's do that again we come back in
now we have a sequence of three and we
ask what is the likely fourth token and
we sample from that and get this one and
now let's say we do it one more time we
take those four we sample and we get
this one and this
13659 uh this is not actually uh 3962 as
we had before so this token is the token
article uh instead so viewing a single
article and so in this case we didn't
exactly reproduce the sequence that we
saw here in the training data so keep in
mind that these systems are stochastic
they have um we're sampling and we're
flipping coins and sometimes we lock out
and we reproduce some like small chunk
of the text and training set but
sometimes we're uh we're getting a token
that was not verbatim part of any of the
documents in the training data so we're
going to get sort of like remixes of the
data that we saw in the training because
at every step of the way we can flip and
get a slightly different token and then
once that token makes it in if you
sample the next one and so on you very
quickly uh start to generate token
streams that are very different from the
token streams that UR
in the training documents so
statistically they will have similar
properties but um they are not identical
to your training data they're kind of
like inspired by the training data and
so in this case we got a slightly
different sequence and why would we get
article you might imagine that article
is a relatively likely token in the
context of bar viewing single Etc and
you can imagine that the word article
followed this context window somewhere
in the training documents uh to some
extent and we just happen to sample it
here at that stage so basically
inference is just uh predicting from
these distributions one at a time we
continue feeding back tokens and getting
the next one and we uh we're always
flipping these coins and depending on
how lucky or unlucky we get um we might
get very different kinds of patterns
depending on how we sample from these
probability distributions so that's
inference so in most common scenarios uh
basically downloading the internet and
tokenizing it is is a pre-processing
step you do that a single time and then
uh once you have your token sequence we
can start training networks and in
Practical cases you would try to train
many different networks of different
kinds of uh settings and different kinds
of arrangements and different kinds of
sizes and so you''ll be doing a lot of
neural network training and um then once
you have a neural network and you train
it and you have some specific set of
parameters that you're happy with um
then you can take the model and you can
do inference and you can actually uh
generate data from the model and when
you're on chat GPT and you're talking
with a model uh that model is trained
and has been trained by open aai many
months ago probably and they have a
specific set of Weights that work well
and when you're talking to the model all
of that is just inference there's no
more training those parameters are held
fixed and you're just talking to the
model sort of uh you're giving it some
of the tokens and it's kind of
completing token sequences and that's
what you're seeing uh generated when you
actually use the model on CH GPT so that
model then just does inference alone so
let's now look at an example of training
an inference that is kind of concrete
and gives you a sense of what this
actually looks like uh when these models
are trained now the example that I would
like to work with and that I'm
particularly fond of is that of opening
eyes gpt2 so GPT uh stands for
generatively pre-trained Transformer and
this is the second iteration of the GPT
series by open AI when you are talking
to chat GPT today the model that is
underlying all of the magic of that
interaction is GPT 4 so the fourth
iteration of that series now gpt2 was
published in 2019 by openi in this paper
that I have right here and the reason I
like gpt2 is that it is the first time
that a recognizably modern stack came
together so um all of the pieces of gpd2
are recognizable today by modern
standards it's just everything has
gotten bigger now I'm not going to be
able to go into the full details of this
paper of course because it is a
technical publication but some of the
details that I would like to highlight
are as follows gpt2 was a Transformer
neural network just like you were just
like the neural networks you would work
with today it was it had 1.6 billion
parameters right so these are the
parameters that we looked at here it
would have 1.6 billion of them today
modern Transformers would have a lot
closer to a trillion or several hundred
billion
probably the maximum context length here
was 1,24 tokens so it is when we are
sampling chunks of Windows of tokens
from the data set we're never taking
more than 1,24 tokens and so when you
are trying to predict the next token in
a sequence you will never have more than
1,24 tokens uh kind of in your context
in order to make that prediction now
this is also tiny by modern standards
today the token uh the context lengths
would be a lot closer to um couple
hundred thousand or maybe even a million
and so you have a lot more context a lot
more tokens in history history and you
can make a lot better prediction about
the next token in the sequence in that
way and finally gpt2 was trained on
approximately 100 billion tokens and
this is also fairly small by modern
standards as I mentioned the fine web
data set that we looked at here the fine
web data set has 15 trillion tokens uh
so 100 billion is is quite
small
now uh I actually tried to reproduce uh
gpt2 for fun as part of this project
called lm. C so you can see my rup of
doing that in this post on GitHub under
the lm. C repository so in particular
the cost of training gpd2 in 2019 what
was estimated to be approximately
$40,000 but today you can do
significantly better than that and in
particular here it took about one day
and about
$600 uh but this wasn't even trying too
hard I think you could really bring this
down to about $100 today now why is it
that the costs have come down so much
well number one these data sets have
gotten a lot better and the way we
filter them extract them and prepare
them has gotten a lot more refined and
so the data set is of just a lot higher
quality so that's one thing but really
the biggest difference is that our
computers have gotten much faster in
terms of the hardware and we're going to
look at that in a second and also the
software for uh running these models and
really squeezing out all all the speed
from the hardware as it is possible uh
that software has also gotten much
better as as everyone has focused on
these models and try to run them very
very
quickly now I'm not going to be able to
go into the full detail of this gpd2
reproduction and this is a long
technical post but I would like to still
give you an intuitive sense for what it
looks like to actually train one of
these models as a researcher like what
are you looking at and what does it look
like what does it feel like so let me
give you a sense of that a little bit
okay so this is what it looks like let
me slide this
over so what I'm doing here is I'm
training a gpt2 model right now
and um what's happening here is that
every single line here like this one is
one update to the model so remember how
here we are um basically making the
prediction better for every one of these
tokens and we are updating these weights
or parameters of the neural net so here
every single line is One update to the
neural network where we change its
parameters by a little bit so that it is
better at predicting next token and
sequence in particular every single line
here is improving the prediction on 1
million tokens in the training set so
we've basically taken 1 million tokens
out of this data set and we've tried to
improve the prediction of that token as
coming next in a sequence on all 1
million of them
simultaneously and at every single one
of these steps we are making an update
to the network for that now the number
to watch closely is this number called
loss and the loss is a single number
that is telling you how well your neural
network is performing right now and it
is created so that low loss is good so
you'll see that the loss is decreasing
as we make more updates to the neural
nut which corresponds to making better
predictions on the next token in a
sequence and so the loss is the number
that you are watching as a neural
network researcher and you are kind of
waiting you're twiddling your thumbs uh
you're drinking coffee and you're making
sure that this looks good so that with
every update your loss is improving and
the network is getting better at
prediction now here you see that we are
processing 1 million tokens per update
each update takes about 7 Seconds
roughly and here we are going to process
a total of 32,000 steps of
optimization so 32,000 steps with 1
million tokens each is about 33 billion
tokens that we are going to process and
we're currently only about 420 step 20
out of 32,000 so we are still only a bit
more than 1% done because I've only been
running this for 10 or 15 minutes or
something like
that now every 20 steps I have
configured this optimization to do
inference so what you're seeing here is
the model is predicting the next token
in a sequence and so you sort of start
it randomly and then you continue
plugging in the tokens so we're running
this inference step and this is the
model sort of predicting the next token
in the sequence and every time you see
something appear that's a new
token um so let's just look at this and
you can see that this is not yet very
coherent and keep in mind that this is
only 1% of the way through training and
so the model is not yet very good at
predicting the next token in the
sequence so what comes out is actually
kind of a little bit of gibberish right
but it still has a little bit of like
local coherence so since she is mine
it's a part of the information should
discuss my father great companions
Gordon showed me sitting over at and Etc
so I know it doesn't look very good but
let's actually scroll up and see what it
looked like when I started the
optimization so all the way here at
step
one so after 20 steps of optimization
you see that what we're getting here is
looks completely random and of course
that's because the model has only had 20
updates to its parameters and so it's
giving you random text because it's a
random Network and so you can see that
at least in comparison to this model is
starting to do much better and indeed if
we waited the entire 32,000 steps the
model will have improved the point that
it's actually uh generating fairly
coherent English uh and the tokens
stream correctly um and uh they they
kind of make up English a a lot
better
um so this has to run for about a day or
two more now and so uh at this stage we
just make sure that the loss is
decreasing everything is looking good um
and we just have to wait
and now um let me turn now to the um
story of the computation that's required
because of course I'm not running this
optimization on my laptop that would be
way too expensive uh because we have to
run this neural network and we have to
improve it and we have we need all this
data and so on so you can't run this too
well on your computer uh because the
network is just too large uh so all of
this is running on the computer that is
out there in the cloud and I want to
basically address the compute side of
the store of training these models and
what that looks like so let's take a
look okay so the computer that I'm
running this optimization on is this 8X
h100 node so there are eight h100s in a
single node or a single computer now I
am renting this computer and it is
somewhere in the cloud I'm not sure
where it is physically actually the
place I like to rent from is called
Lambda but there are many other
companies who provide this service so
when you scroll down you can see that uh
they have some on demand pricing for
um sort of computers that have these uh
h100s which are gpus and I'm going to
show you what they look like in a second
but on demand 8times Nvidia h100 uh
GPU this machine comes for $3 per GPU
per hour for example so you can rent
these and then you get a machine in a
cloud and you can uh go in and you can
train these
models and these uh gpus they look like
this so this is one h100 GPU uh this is
kind of what it looks like and you slot
this into your computer and gpus are
this uh perfect fit for training your
networks because they are very
computationally expensive but they
display a lot of parallelism in the
computation so you can have many
independent workers kind of um working
all at the same time in solving uh the
matrix multiplication that's under the
hood of training these neural
networks so this is just one of these
h100s but actually you would put them
you would put multiple of them together
so you could stack eight of them into a
single node and then you can stack
multiple nodes into an entire data
center or an entire system
so when we look at a data
center can't spell when we look at a
data center we start to see things that
look like this right so we have one GPU
goes to eight gpus goes to a single
system goes to many systems and so these
are the bigger data centers and there of
course would be much much more expensive
um and what's happening is that all the
big tech companies really desire these
gpus so they can train all these
language models because they are so
powerful and that has is fundamentally
what has driven the stock price of
Nvidia to be $3.4 trillion today as an
example and why Nvidia has kind of
exploded so this is the Gold Rush the
Gold Rush is getting the gpus getting
enough of them so they can all
collaborate to perform this optimization
and they're what are they all doing
they're all collaborating to predict the
next token on a data set like the fine
web data
set this is the computational workflow
that that basically is extremely
expensive the more gpus you have the
more tokens you can try to predict and
improve on and you're going to process
this data set faster and you can iterate
faster and get a bigger Network and
train a bigger Network and so on so this
is what all those machines are look like
are uh are doing and this is why all of
this is such a big deal and for example
this is a
article from like about a month ago or
so this is why it's a big deal that for
example Elon Musk is getting 100,000
gpus uh in a single Data Center and all
of these gpus are extremely expensive
are going to take a ton of power and all
of them are just trying to predict the
next token in the sequence and improve
the network uh by doing so and uh get
probably a lot more coherent text than
what we're seeing here a lot faster okay
so unfortunately I do not have a couple
10 or hundred million of dollars to
spend on training a really big model
like this but luckily we can turn to
some big tech companies who train these
models routinely and release some of
them once they are done training so
they've spent a huge amount of compute
to train this network and they release
the network at the end of the
optimization so it's very useful because
they've done a lot of compute for that
so there are many companies who train
these models routinely but actually not
many of them release uh these what's
called base models so the model that
comes out at the end here is is what's
called a base model what is a base model
it's a token simulator right it's an
internet text token simulator and so
that is not by itself useful yet because
what we want is what's called an
assistant we want to ask questions and
have it respond to answers these models
won't do that they just uh create sort
of remixes of the internet they dream
internet pages so the base models are
not very often released because they're
kind of just only a step one of a few
other steps that we still need to take
to get in system
however a few releases have been made so
as an example the gbt2 model released
the 1.6 billion sorry 1.5 billion model
back in 2019 and this gpt2 model is a
base model now what is a model release
what does it look like to release these
models so this is the gpt2 repository on
GitHub well you need two things
basically to release model number one we
need the um python code usually that
describes the sequence of operations in
detail that they make in their model so
um if you remember
back this
Transformer the sequence of steps that
are taken here in this neural network is
what is being described by this code so
this code is sort of implementing the
what's called forward pass of this
neural network so we need the specific
details of exactly how they wired up
that neural network so this is just
computer code and it's usually just a
couple hundred lines of code it's not
it's not that crazy and uh this is all
fairly understandable and usually fairly
standard what's not standard are the
parameters that's where the actual value
is what are the parameters of this
neural network because there's 1.6
billion of them and we need the correct
setting or a really good setting and so
that's why in addition to this source
code they release the parameters which
in this case is roughly 1.5 billion
parameters and these are just numbers so
it's one single list of 1.5 billion
numbers the precise and good setting of
all the knobs such that the tokens come
out
well so uh you need those two things to
get a base model
release
now gpt2 was released but that's
actually a fairly old model as I
mentioned so actually the model we're
going to turn to is called llama 3 and
that's the one that I would like to show
you next so llama 3 so gpt2 again was
1.6 billion parameters trained on 100
billion tokens Lama 3 is a much bigger
model and much more modern model it is
released and trained by meta and it is a
45 billion parameter model trained on 15
trillion tokens in very much the same
way just much much
bigger um and meta has also made a
release of llama 3 and that was part of
this
paper so with this paper that goes into
a lot of detail the biggest base model
that they released is the Lama 3.1 4.5
405 billion parameter model so this is
the base model and then in addition to
the base model you see here
foreshadowing for later sections of the
video they also released the instruct
model and the instruct means that this
is an assistant you can ask it questions
and it will give you answers we still
have yet to cover that part later for
now let's just look at this base model
this token simulator and let's play with
it and try to think about you know what
is this thing and how does it work and
um what do we get at the end of this
optimization if you let this run Until
the End uh for a very big neural network
on a lot of data so my favorite place to
interact with the base models is this um
company called hyperbolic which is
basically serving the base model of the
405b Llama 3.1 so when you go to the
website and I think you may have to
register and so on make sure that in the
models make sure that you are using
llama 3.1 405 billion base it must be
the base model and then here let's say
the max tokens is how many tokens we're
going to be gener rating so let's just
decrease this to be a bit less just so
we don't waste compute we just want the
next 128 tokens and leave the other
stuff alone I'm not going to go into the
full detail here um now fundamentally
what's going to happen here is identical
to what happens here during inference
for us so this is just going to continue
the token sequence of whatever you
prefix you're going to give it so I want
to first show you that this model here
is not yet an assistant so you can for
example ask it what is 2 plus 2 it's not
going to tell you oh it's four uh what
else can I help you with it's not going
to do that because what is 2 plus 2 is
going to be tokenized and then those
tokens just act as a prefix and then
what the model is going to do now is
just going to get the probability for
the next token and it's just a glorified
autocomplete it's a very very expensive
autocomplete of what comes next um
depending on the statistics of what it
saw in its training documents which are
basically web
pages so let's just uh hit enter to see
what tokens it comes up with as a
continuation okay so here it kind of
actually answered the question and
started to go off into some
philosophical territory uh let's try it
again so let me copy and paste and let's
try again from scratch what is 2 plus
two so okay so it just goes off again so
notice one more thing that I want to
stress is that the system uh I think
every time you put it in it just kind of
starts from scratch
so it doesn't uh the system here is
stochastic so for the same prefix of
tokens we're always getting a different
answer and the reason for that is that
we get this probity distribution and we
sample from it and we always get
different samples and we sort of always
go into a different territory uh
afterwards so here in this case um I
don't know what this is let's try one
more
time so it just continues on so it's
just doing the stuff that it's saw on
the internet right um and it's just kind
of like regurgitating those uh
statistical
patterns so first things it's not an
assistant yet it's a token autocomplete
and second it is a stochastic system now
the crucial thing is that even though
this model is not yet by itself very
useful for a lot of applications just
yet um it is still very useful because
in the task of predicting the next token
in the sequence the model has learned a
lot about the world and it has stored
all that knowledge in the parameters of
the network so remember that our text
looked like this right internet web
pages and now all of this is sort of
compressed in the weights of the network
so you can think of um these 405 billion
parameters is a kind of compression of
the internet you can think of the
45 billion parameters is kind of like a
zip file uh but it's not a loss less
compression it's a loss C compression
we're kind of like left with kind of a
gal of the internet and we can generate
from it right now we can elicit some of
this knowledge by prompting the base
model uh accordingly so for example
here's a prompt that might work to
elicit some of that knowledge that's
hiding in the parameters here's my top
10 list of the top landmarks to see in
the
pairs
um and I'm doing it this way because I'm
trying to Prime the model to now
continue this list so let's see if that
works when I press
enter okay so you see that it started a
list and it's now kind of giving me some
of those
landmarks and now notice that it's
trying to give a lot of information here
now you might not be able to actually
fully trust some of the information here
remember that this is all just a
recollection of some of the internet
documents and so the things that occur
very frequently in the internet data are
probably more likely to be remembered
correctly compared to things that happen
very infrequently so you can't fully
trust some of the things that and some
of the information that is here because
it's all just a vague recollection of
Internet documents because the
information is not stored explicitly in
any of the parameters it's all just the
recollection that said we did get
something that is probably approximately
correct and I don't actually have the
expertise to verify that this is roughly
correct but you see that we've elicited
a lot of the knowledge of the model and
this knowledge is not precise and exact
this knowledge is vague and
probabilistic and statistical and the
kinds of things that occur often are the
kinds of things that are more likely to
be remembered um in the model now I want
to show you a few more examples of this
model's Behavior the first thing I want
to show you is this example I went to
the Wikipedia page for zebra and let me
just copy paste the first uh even one
sentence
here and let me put it here now when I
click enter what kind of uh completion
are we going to get so let me just hit
enter there are three living species
etc etc what the model is producing here
is an exact regurgitation of this
Wikipedia entry it is reciting this
Wikipedia entry purely from memory and
this memory is stored in its parameters
and so it is possible that at some point
in these 512 tokens the model will uh
stray away from the Wikipedia entry but
you can see that it has huge chunks of
it memorized here uh let me see for
example if this sentence
occurs by now okay so this so we're
still on track let me check
here okay we're still on
track it will eventually uh stray
away okay so this thing is just recited
to a very large extent it will
eventually deviate uh because it won't
be able to remember exactly now the
reason that this happens is because
these models can be extremely good at
memorization and usually this is not
what you want in the final model and
this is something called regurgitation
and it's usually undesirable to site uh
things uh directly uh that you have
trained on now the reason that this
happens actually is because for a lot of
documents like for example Wikipedia
when these documents are deemed to be of
very high quality as a source like for
example Wikipedia it is very often uh
the case that when you train the model
you will preferentially sample from
those sources so basically the model has
probably done a few epochs on this data
meaning that it has seen this web page
like maybe probably 10 times or so and
it's a bit like you like when you read
some kind of a text many many times say
you read something a 100 times uh then
you'll be able to recite it and it's
very similar for this model if it sees
something way too often it's going to be
able to recite it later from memory
except these models can be a lot more
efficient um like per presentation than
human so probably it's only seen this
Wikipedia entry 10 times but basically
it has remembered this article exactly
in its parameters okay the next thing I
want to show you is something that the
model has definitely not seen during its
training so for example if we go to the
paper uh and then we navigate to the
pre-training data we'll see here that uh
the data set has a knowledge cut off
until the end of 2023 so it will not
have seen documents after this point and
certainly it has not seen anything about
the 2024 election and how it turned out
now if we Prime the model with the
tokens from the future it will continue
the token sequence and it will just take
its best guess according to the
knowledge that it has in its own
parameters so let's take a look at what
that could look like
so the Republican Party kit
Trump okay president of the United
States from
2017 and let's see what it says after
this point so for example the model will
have to guess at the running mate and
who it's against Etc so let's hit
enter so here thingss that Mike Pence
was the running mate instead of JD Vance
and the ticket was against Hillary
Clinton and Tim Kane so this is kind of
a interesting parallel universe
potentially of what could have happened
happened according to the LM let's get a
different sample so the identical prompt
and let's
resample so here the running mate was
Ronda santis and they ran against Joe
Biden and Camala Harris so this is again
a different parallel universe so the
model will take educated guesses and it
will continue the token sequence based
on this knowledge um and it will just
kind of like all of what we're seeing
here is what's called hallucination the
model is just taking its best guess uh
in a probalistic manner the next thing I
would like to show you is that even
though this is a base model and not yet
an assistant model it can still be
utilized in Practical applications if
you are clever with your prompt design
so here's something that we would call a
few shot
prompt so what it is here is that I have
10 words or 10 pairs and each pair is a
word of English column and then a the
translation in Korean and we have 10 of
them and what the model does here is at
the end we have teacher column and then
here's where we're going to do a
completion of say just five tokens and
these models have what we call in
context learning abilities and what
that's referring to is that as it is
reading this context it is learning sort
of in
place that there's some kind of a
algorithmic pattern going on in my data
and it knows to continue that pattern
and this is called kind of like Inc
context learning so it takes on the role
of a
translator and when we hit uh completion
we see that the teacher translation is
Sim which is correct um and so this is
how you can build apps by being clever
with your prompting even though we still
just have a base model for now and it
relies on what we call this um uh in
context learning ability and it is done
by constructing what's called a few shot
prompt okay and finally I want to show
you that there is a clever way to
actually instantiate a whole language
model assistant just by prompting and
the trick to it is that we're structure
a prompt to look like a web page that is
a conversation between a helpful AI
assistant and a human and then the model
will continue that conversation so
actually to write the prompt I turned to
chat gbt itself which is kind of meta
but I told it I want to create an llm
assistant but all I have is the base
model so can you please write my um uh
prompt and this is what it came up with
which is actually quite good so here's a
conversation between an AI assistant and
a human
the AI assistant is knowledgeable
helpful capable of answering wide
variety of questions Etc and then here
it's not enough to just give it a sort
of description it works much better if
you create this fot prompt so here's a
few terms of human assistant human
assistant and we have uh you know a few
turns of conversation and then here at
the end is we're going to be putting the
actual query that we like so let me copy
paste this into the base model prompt
and now let me do human column and this
is where we put our actual prompt why is
the sky
blue and uh let's uh
run assistant the sky appears blue due
to the phenomenon called R lights
scattering etc etc so you see that the
base model is just continuing the
sequence but because the sequence looks
like this conversation it takes on that
role but it is a little subtle because
here it just uh you know it ends the
assistant and then just you know
hallucinate Ates the next question by
the human Etc so it'll just continue
going on and on uh but you can see that
we have sort of accomplished the task
and if you just took this why is the sky
blue and if we just refresh this and put
it here then of course we don't expect
this to work with a base model right
we're just going to who knows what we're
going to get okay we're just going to
get more
questions okay so this is one way to
create an assistant even though you may
only have a base model okay so this is
the kind of brief summary of the things
we talked about over the last few
minutes now let me zoom out
here and this is kind of like what we've
talked about so far we wish to train LM
assistants like chpt we've discussed the
first stage of that which is the
pre-training stage and we saw that
really what it comes down to is we take
Internet documents we break them up into
these tokens these atoms of little text
chunks and then we predict token
sequences using neural networks the
output of this entire stage is this base
model it is the setting of The
parameters of this network and this base
model is basically an internet document
simulator on the token level so it can
just uh it can generate token sequences
that have the same kind of like
statistics as Internet documents and we
saw that we can use it in some
applications but we actually need to do
better we want an assistant we want to
be able to ask questions and we want the
model to give us answers and so we need
to now go into the second stage which is
called the post-training stage so we
take our base model our internet
document simulator and hand it off to
post training so we're now going to
discuss a few ways to do what's called
post training of these models these
stages in post training are going to be
computationally much less expensive most
of the computational work all of the
massive data centers um and all of the
sort of heavy compute and millions of
dollars are the pre-training stage but
now we go into the slightly cheaper but
still extremely important stage called
post trining where we turn this llm
model into an assistant so let's take a
look at how we can get our model to not
sample internet documents but to give
answers to questions so in other words
what we want to do is we want to start
thinking about conversations and these
are conversations that can be multi-turn
so so uh there can be multiple turns and
they are in the simplest case a
conversation between a human and an
assistant and so for example we can
imagine the conversation could look
something like this when a human says
what is 2 plus2 the assistant should re
respond with something like 2 plus 2 is
4 when a human follows up and says what
if it was star instead of a plus
assistant could respond with something
like
this um and similar here this is another
example showing that the assistant could
also have some kind of a personality
here uh that it's kind of like nice and
then here in the third example I'm
showing that when a human is asking for
something that we uh don't wish to help
with we can produce what's called
refusal we can say that we cannot help
with that so in other words what we want
to do now is we want to think through
how in a system should interact with the
human and we want to program the
assistant and Its Behavior in these
conversations now because this is neural
networks we're not going to be
programming these explicitly in code
we're not going to be able to program
the assistant in that way because this
is neural networks everything is done
through neural network training on data
sets and so because of that we are going
to be implicitly programming the
assistant by creating data sets of
conversations so these are three
independent examples of conversations in
a data dat set an actual data set and
I'm going to show you examples will be
much larger it could have hundreds of
thousands of conversations that are
multi- turn very long Etc and would
cover a diverse breath of topics but
here I'm only showing three examples but
the way this works basically is uh a
assistant is being programmed by example
and where is this data coming from like
2 * 2al 4 same as 2 plus 2 Etc where
does that come from this comes from
Human labelers so we will basically give
human labelers some conversational
context and we will ask them to um
basically give the ideal assistant
response in this situation and a human
will write out the ideal response for an
assistant in any situation and then
we're going to get the model to
basically train on this and to imitate
those kinds of
responses so the way this works then is
we are going to take our base model
which we produced in the preing stage
and this base model was trained on
internet documents we're now going to
take that data set of internet documents
and we're gonna throw it out and we're
going to substitute a new data set and
that's going to be a data set of
conversations and we're going to
continue training the model on these
conversations on this new data set of
conversations and what happens is that
the model will very rapidly adjust and
will sort of like learn the statistics
of how this assistant responds to human
queries and then later during inference
we'll be able to basically um Prime the
assistant and get the response and it
will be imitating what the humans will
human labelers would do in that
situation if that makes sense so we're
going to see examples of that and this
is going to become bit more concrete I
also wanted to mention that this
post-training stage we're going to
basically just continue training the
model but um the pre-training stage can
in practice take roughly three months of
training on many thousands of computers
the post-training stage will typically
be much shorter like 3 hours for example
um and that's because the data set of
conversations that we're going to create
here manually is much much smaller than
the data set of text on the internet and
so this training will be very short but
fundamentally we're just going to take
our base model we're going to continue
training using the exact same algorithm
the exact same everything except we're
swapping out the data set for
conversations so the questions now are
what are these conversations how do we
represent them how do we get the model
to see conversations instead of just raw
text and then what are the outcomes of
um this kind of training and what do you
get in a certain like psychological
sense uh when we talk about the model so
let's turn to those questions now so
let's start by talking about the
tokenization of conversations everything
in these models has to be turned into
tokens because everything is just about
token sequences so how do we turn
conversations into token sequences is
the question and so for that we need to
design some kind of ending coding and uh
this is kind of similar to maybe if
you're familiar you don't have to be
with for example the TCP IP packet in um
on the internet there are precise rules
and protocols for how you represent
information how everything is structured
together so that you have all this kind
of data laid out in a way that is
written out on a paper and that everyone
can agree on and so it's the same thing
now happening in llms we need some kind
of data structures and we need to have
some rules around how these data
structures like conversations get
encoded and decoded to and from tokens
and so I want to show you now how I
would
recreate uh this conversation in the
token space so if you go to Tech
tokenizer
I can take that conversation and this is
how it is represented in uh for the
language model so here we have we are
iterating a user and an assistant in
this two- turn
conversation and what you're seeing here
is it looks ugly but it's actually
relatively simple the way it gets turned
into a token sequence here at the end is
a little bit complicated but at the end
this conversation between a user and
assistant ends up being 49 tokens it is
a one-dimensional sequence of 49 tokens
and these are the tokens
okay and all the different llms will
have a slightly different format or
protocols and it's a little bit of a
wild west right now but for example GPT
40 does it in the following way you have
this special token called imore start
and this is short for IM imaginary
monologue uh the
start then you have to specify um I
don't actually know why it's called that
to be honest then you have to specify
whose turn it is so for example user
which is a token 4
28 then you have internal monologue
separator and then it's the exact
question so the tokens of the question
and then you have to close it so I am
end the end of the imaginary monologue
so
basically the question from a user of
what is 2 plus two ends up being the
token sequence of these tokens and now
the important thing to mention here is
that IM start this is not text right IM
start is a special token that gets added
it's a new token and um this token has
never been trained on so far it is a new
token that we create in a post-training
stage and we introduce and so these
special tokens like IM seep IM start Etc
are introduced and interspersed with
text so that they sort of um get the
model to learn that hey this is a the
start of a turn for who is it start of
the turn for the start of the turn is
for the user and then this is what the
user says and then the user ends and
then it's a new start of a turn and it
is by the assistant and then what does
the assistant say well these are the
tokens of what the assistant says Etc
and so this conversation is not turned
into the sequence of tokens the specific
details here are not actually that
important all I'm trying to show you in
concrete terms is that our conversations
which we think of as kind of like a
structured object end up being turned
via some encoding into onedimensional
sequences of tokens and so because this
is one dimensional sequence of tokens we
can apply all the stuff that we applied
before now it's just a sequence of
tokens and now we can train a language
model on it and so we're just predicting
the next token in a sequence uh just
like before and um we can represent and
train on conversations and then what
does it look like at test time during
inference so say we've trained a model
and we've trained a model on these kinds
of data sets of conversations and now we
want to
inference so during inference what does
this look like when you're on on chash
apt well you come to chash apt and you
have say like a dialogue with it and the
way this works is
basically um say that this was already
filled in so like what is 2 plus 2 2
plus 2 is four and now you issue what if
it was times I am end and what basically
ends up happening um on the servers of
open AI or something like that is they
put in I start assistant I amep and this
is where they end it right here so they
construct this context and now they
start sampling from the model so it's at
this stage that they will go to the
model and say okay what is a good for
sequence what is a good first token what
is a good second token what is a good
third token and this is where the LM
takes over and creates a response like
for example response that looks
something like this but it doesn't have
to be identical to this but it will have
the flavor of this if this kind of a
conversation was in the data set so um
that's roughly how the protocol Works
although the details of this protocol
are not important so again my goal is
that just to show you that everything
ends up being just a one-dimensional
token sequence so we can apply
everything we've already seen but we're
now training on conversations and we're
now uh basically generating
conversations as well okay so now I
would like to turn to what these data
sets look like in practice the first
paper that I would like to show you and
the first effort in this direction is
this paper from openai in 2022 and this
paper was called instruct GPT or the
technique that they developed and this
was the first time that opena has kind
of talked about how you can take
language models and fine-tune them on
conversations and so this paper has a
number of details that I would like to
take you through so the first stop I
would like to make is in section 3.4
where they talk about the human
contractors that they hired uh in this
case from upwork or through scale AI to
uh construct these conversations and so
there are human labelers involved whose
job it is professionally to create these
conversations and these labelers are
asked to come up with prompts and then
they are asked to also complete the
ideal assistant responses and so these
are the kinds of prompts that people
came up with so these are human labelers
so list five ideas for how to regain
enthusiasm for my career what are the
top 10 science fiction books I should
read next and there's many different
types of uh kind of prompts here so
translate this sentence from uh to
Spanish Etc and so there's many things
here that people came up with they first
come up with the prompt and then they
also uh answer that prompt and they give
the ideal assistant response now how do
they know what is the ideal assistant
response that they should write for
these prompts so when we scroll down a
little bit further we see that here we
have this excerpt of labeling
instructions uh that are given to the
human labelers so the company that is
developing the language model like for
example open AI writes up labeling
instructions for how the humans should
create ideal responses and so here for
example is an excerpt uh of these kinds
of labeling instruction instructions on
High level you're asking people to be
helpful truthful and harmless and you
can pause the video if you'd like to see
more here but on a high level basically
just just answer try to be helpful try
to be truthful and don't answer
questions that we don't want um kind of
the system to handle uh later in chat
gbt and so roughly speaking the company
comes up with the labeling instructions
usually they are not this short usually
there are hundreds of pages and people
have to study them professionally and
then they write out the ideal assistant
responses uh following those labeling
instructions so this is a very human
heavy process as it was described in
this paper now the data set for instruct
GPT was never actually released by openi
but we do have some open- Source um
reproductions that were're trying to
follow this kind of a setup and collect
their own data so one that I'm familiar
with for example is the effort of open
Assistant from a while back and this is
just one of I think many examples but I
just want to show you an example so
here's so these were people on the
internet that were asked to basically
create these conversations similar to
what um open I did with human labelers
and so here's an entry of a person who
came up with this BR can you write a
short introduction to the relevance of
the term
manop uh in economics please use
examples Etc and then the same person or
potentially a different person will
write up the response so here's the
assistant response to this and so then
the same person or different person will
actually write out this ideal
response and then this is an example of
maybe how the conversation could
continue now explain it to a dog and
then you can try to come up with a
slightly a simpler explanation or
something like that now this then
becomes the label and we end up training
on this so what happens during training
is that um of course we're not going to
have a full coverage of all the possible
questions that um the model will
encounter at test time during inference
we can't possibly cover all the possible
prompts that people are going to be
asking in the future but if we have a
like a data set of a few of these
examples then the model during training
will start to take on this Persona of
this helpful truthful harmless assistant
and it's all programmed by example and
so these are all examples of behavior
and if you have conversations of these
example behaviors and you have enough of
them like 100,00 and you train on it the
model sort of starts to understand the
statistical pattern and it kind of takes
on this personality of this
assistant now it's possible that when
you get the exact same question like
this at test time it's possible that the
answer will be recited as exactly what
was in the training set but more likely
than that is that the model will kind of
like do something of a similar Vibe um
and we will understand that this is the
kind of answer that you want um so
that's what we're doing we're
programming the system um by example and
the system adopts statistically this
Persona of this helpful truthful
harmless assistant which is kind of like
reflected in the labeling instructions
that the company creates now I want to
show you that the state-of-the-art has
kind of advanced in the last 2 or 3
years uh since the instr GPT paper so in
particular it's not very common for
humans to be doing all the heavy lifting
just by themselves anymore and that's
because we now have language models and
these language models are helping us
create these data sets and conversations
so it is very rare that the people will
like literally just write out the
response from scratch it is a lot more
likely that they will use an existing
llm to basically like uh come up with an
answer and then they will edit it or
things like that so there's many
different ways in which now llms have
started to kind of permeate this
posttraining Set uh stack and llms are
basically used pervasively to help
create these massive data sets of
conversations so I don't want to show
like Ultra chat is one um such example
of like a more modern data set of
conversations it is to a very large
extent synthetic but uh I believe
there's some human involvement I could
be wrong with that usually there will be
a little bit of human but there will be
a huge amount of synthetic help um and
this is all kind of like uh constructed
in different ways and Ultra chat is just
one example of many sft data sets that
currently exist and the only thing I
want to show you is that uh these data
sets have now millions of conversations
uh these conversations are mostly
synthetic but they're probably edited to
some extent by humans and they span a
huge diversity of sort of
um uh areas and so on so these are
fairly extensive artifacts by now and
there's all these like sft mixtures as
they're called so you have a mixture of
like lots of different types and sources
and it's partially synthetic partially
human and it's kind of like um gone in
that direction since uh but roughly
speaking we still have sft data sets
they're made up of conversations we're
training on them um just like we did
before and
uh I guess like the last thing to note
is that I want to dispel a little bit of
the magic of talking to an AI like when
you go to chat GPT and you give it a
question and then you hit enter uh what
is coming back is kind of like
statistically aligned with what's
happening in the training set and these
training sets I mean they really just
have a seed in humans following labeling
instructions so what are you actually
talking to in chat GPT or how should you
think about it well it's not coming from
some magical AI like roughly speaking
it's coming from something that is
statistically imitating human labelers
which comes from labeling instructions
written by these companies and so you're
kind of imitating this uh you're kind of
getting um it's almost as if you're
asking human labeler and imagine that
the answer that is given to you uh from
chbt is some kind of a simulation of a
human labeler uh and it's kind of like
asking what would a human labeler say in
this kind of a conversation
and uh it's not just like this human
labeler is not just like a random person
from the internet because these
companies actually hire experts so for
example when you are asking questions
about code and so on the human labelers
that would be in um involved in creation
of these conversation data sets they
will usually be usually be educated
expert people and you're kind of like
asking a question of like a simulation
of those people if that makes sense so
you're not talking to a magical AI
you're talking to an average labeler
this average labeler is probably fairly
highly skilled
but you're talking to kind of like an
instantaneous simulation of that kind of
a person that would be hired uh in the
construction of these data sets so let
me give you one more specific example
before we move on for example when I go
to chpt and I say recommend the top five
landmarks who see in Paris and then I
hit
enter
uh okay here we go okay when I hit enter
what's coming out here how do I think
about it well it's not some kind of a
magical AI that has gone out and
researched all the landmarks and then
ranked them using its infinite
intelligence Etc what I'm getting is a
statistical simulation of a labeler that
was hired by open AI you can think about
it roughly in that way and so if this
specific um question is in the
posttraining data set somewhere at open
aai then I'm very likely to see an
answer that is probably very very
similar to what that human labeler would
have put down
for those five landmarks how does the
human labeler come up with this well
they go off and they go on the internet
and they kind of do their own little
research for 20 minutes and they just
come up with a list right now so if they
come up with this list and this is in
the data set I'm probably very likely to
see what they submitted as the correct
answer from the assistant now if this
specific query is not part of the post
training data set then what I'm getting
here is a little bit more emergent uh
because uh the model kind of understands
the statistically
um the kinds of landmarks that are in
this training set are usually the
prominent landmarks the landmarks that
people usually want to see the kinds of
landmarks that are usually uh very often
talked about on the internet and
remember that the model already has a
ton of Knowledge from its pre-training
on the internet so it's probably seen a
ton of conversations about Paris about
landmarks about the kinds of things that
people like to see and so it's the
pre-training knowledge that has then
combined with the postering data set
that results in this kind of an
imitation um
so that's uh that's roughly how you can
kind of think about what's happening
behind the scenes here in in this
statistical sense okay now I want to
turn to the topic of llm psychology as I
like to call it which is what are sort
of the emergent cognitive effects of the
training pipeline that we have for these
models so in particular the first one I
want to talk to is of course
hallucinations so you might be familiar
with model hallucinations it's when llms
make stuff up they just totally
fabricate information Etc and it's a big
problem with llm assistants it is a
problem that existed to a large extent
with early models uh from many years ago
and I think the problem has gotten a bit
better uh because there are some
medications that I'm going to go into in
a second for now let's just try to
understand where these hallucinations
come from so here's a specific example
of a few uh of three conversations that
you might think you have in your
training set and um these are pretty
reasonable conversations that you could
imagine being in the training set so
like for example who is Cruz well Tom
Cruz is an famous actor American actor
and producer Etc who is John baraso this
turns out to be a us senetor for example
who is genis Khan well genis Khan was
blah blah blah and so this is what your
conversations could look like at
training time now the problem with this
is that when the human is writing the
correct answer for the assistant in each
one of these cases uh the human either
like knows who this person is or they
research them on the Internet and they
come in and they write this response
that kind of has this like confident
tone of an answer and what happens
basically is that at test time when you
ask for someone who is this is a totally
random name that I totally came up with
and I don't think this person exists um
as far as I know I just Tred to generate
it randomly the problem is when we ask
who is Orson kovats the problem is that
the assistant will not just tell you oh
I don't know even if the assistant and
the language model itself might know
inside its features inside its
activations inside of its brain sort of
it might know that this person is like
not someone that um that is that it's
familiar with even if some part of the
network kind of knows that in some sense
the uh saying that oh I don't know who
this is is is not going to happen
because the model statistically imitates
is training set in the training set the
questions of the form who is blah are
confidently answered with the correct
answer and so it's going to take on the
style of the answer and it's going to do
its best it's going to give you
statistically the most likely guess and
it's just going to basically make stuff
up because these models again we just
talked about it is they don't have
access to the internet they're not doing
research these are statistical token
tumblers as I call them uh is just
trying to sample the next token in the
sequence and it's going to basically
make stuff up so let's take a look at
what this looks
like I have here what's called the
inference playground from hugging face
and I am on purpose picking on a model
called Falcon 7B which is an old model
this is a few years ago now so it's an
older model So It suffers from
hallucinations and as I mentioned this
has improved over time recently but
let's say who is Orson kovats let's ask
Falcon 7B instruct
run oh yeah Orson kovat is an American
author and science uh fiction writer
okay this is totally false it's
hallucination let's try again these are
statistical systems right so we can
resample this time Orson kovat is a
fictional character from this 1950s TV
show it's total BS right let's try again
he's a former minor league baseball
player okay so basically the model
doesn't know and it's given us lots of
different answers because it doesn't
know it's just kind of like sampling
from these probabilities the model
starts with the tokens who is oron
kovats assistant and then it comes in
here and it's get it's getting these
probabilities and it's just sampling
from the probabilities and it just like
comes up with stuff and the stuff is
actually
statistically consistent with the style
of the answer in its training set and
it's just doing that but you and I
experiened it as a madeup factual
knowledge but keep in mind that uh the
model basically doesn't know and it's
just imitating the format of the answer
and it's not going to go off and look it
up uh because it's just imitating again
the answer so how can we uh mitigate
this because for example when we go to
chat apt and I say who is oron kovats
and I'm now asking the stateoftheart
state-of-the-art model from open AI
this model will tell
you oh so this model is actually is even
smarter because you saw very briefly it
said searching the web uh we're going to
cover this later um it's actually trying
to do tool use and
uh kind of just like came up with some
kind of a story but I want to just who
or Kovach did not use any tools I don't
want it to do web
search there's a wellknown historical or
public figure named or oron kovats so
this model is not going to make up stuff
this model knows that it doesn't know
and it tells you that it doesn't appear
to be a person that this model knows so
somehow we sort of improved
hallucinations even though they clearly
are an issue in older models and it
makes totally uh sense why you would be
getting these kinds of answers if this
is what your training set looks like so
how do we fix this okay well clearly we
need some examples in our data set that
where the correct answer for the
assistant is that the model doesn't know
about some particular fact but we only
need to have those answers be produced
in the cases where the model actually
doesn't know and so the question is how
do we know what the model knows or
doesn't know well we can empirically
probe the model to figure that out so
let's take a look at for example how
meta uh dealt with hallucinations for
the Llama 3 series of models as an
example so in this paper that they
published from meta we can go into
hallucinations
which they call here factuality and they
describe the procedure by which they
basically interrogate the model to
figure out what it knows and doesn't
know to figure out sort of like the
boundary of its knowledge and then they
add examples to the training set where
for the things where the model doesn't
know them the correct answer is that the
model doesn't know them which sounds
like a very easy thing to do in
principle but this roughly fixes the
issue and the the reason it fixes the
issue is
because remember like the model might
actually have a pretty good model of its
self knowledge inside the network so
remember we looked at the network and
all these neurons inside the network you
might imagine that there's a neuron
somewhere in the network that sort of
like lights up for when the model is
uncertain but the problem is that the
activation of that neuron is not
currently wired up to the model actually
saying in words that it doesn't know so
even though the internal of the neural
network no because there's some neurons
that represent that the model uh will
not surface that it will instead take
its best guess so that it sounds
confident um just like it sees in a
training set so we need to basically
interrogate the model and allow it to
say I don't know in the cases that it
doesn't know so let me take you through
what meta roughly does so basically what
they do is here I have an example uh
Dominic kek is uh the featured article
today so I just went there randomly and
what they do is basically they take a
random document in a training set and
they take a paragraph and then they use
an llm to construct questions about that
paragraph so for example I did that with
chat GPT
here so I said here's a paragraph from
this document generate three specific
factual questions based on this
paragraph and give me the questions and
the answers and so the llms are already
good enough to create and reframe this
information so if the information is in
the context window um of this llm this
actually works pretty well it doesn't
have to rely on its memory it's right
there in the context window and so it
can basically reframe that information
with fairly high accuracy so for example
can generate questions for us like for
which team did he play here's the answer
how many cups did he win Etc and now
what we have to do is we have some
question and answers and now we want to
interrogate the model so roughly
speaking what we'll do is we'll take our
questions and we'll go to our model
which would be uh say llama uh in meta
but let's just interrogate mol 7B here
as an example that's another model so
does this model know about this answer
let's take a
look uh so he played for Buffalo Sabers
right so the model knows and the the way
that you can programmatically decide is
basically we're going to take this
answer from the model and we're going to
compare it to the correct answer and
again the model model are good enough to
do this automatically so there's no
humans involved here we can take uh
basically the answer from the model and
we can use another llm judge to check if
that is correct according to this answer
and if it is correct that means that the
model probably knows so what we're going
to do is we're going to do this maybe a
few times so okay it knows it's Buffalo
Savers let's drag
in um Buffalo Sabers let's try one more
time Buffalo Sabers so we asked three
times about this factual question and
the model seems to know so everything is
great now let's try the second question
how many Stanley Cups did he
win and again let's interrogate the
model about that and the correct answer
is
two so um here the model claims that he
won um four times which is not correct
right it doesn't match two so the model
doesn't know it's making stuff up let's
try again
um so here the model again it's kind of
like making stuff up right let's
Dragon here it says did he did not even
did not win during his career so
obviously the model doesn't know and the
way we can programmatically tell again
is we interrogate the model three times
and we compare its answers maybe three
times five times whatever it is to the
correct answer and if the model doesn't
know then we know that the model doesn't
know this question
and then what we do is we take this
question we create a new conversation in
the training set so we're going to add a
new conversation training set and when
the question is how many Stanley Cups
did he win the answer is I'm sorry I
don't know or I don't remember and
that's the correct answer for this
question because we interrogated the
model and we saw that that's the case if
you do this for many different types of
uh questions for many different types of
documents you are giving the model an
opportunity to in its training set
refuse to say based on its knowledge and
if you just have a few examples of that
in your training set the model will know
um and and has the opportunity to learn
the association of this knowledge-based
refusal to this internal neuron
somewhere in its Network that we presume
exists and empirically this turns out to
be probably the case and it can learn
that Association that hey when this
neuron of uncertainty is high then I
actually don't know and I'm allowed to
say that I'm sorry but I don't think I
remember this Etc and if you have these
uh examples in your training set then
this is a large mitigation for
hallucination and that's roughly
speaking why chpt is able to do stuff
like this as well so these are kinds of
uh mitigations that people have
implemented and that have improved the
factuality issue over time okay so I've
described mitigation number one for
basically mitigating the hallucinations
issue now we can actually do much better
than that uh it's instead of just saying
that we don't know uh we can introduce
an additional mitigation number two to
give the llm an opportunity to be
factual and actually answer the question
now what do you and I do if I was to ask
you a factual question and you don't
know uh what would you do um in order to
answer the question well you could uh go
off and do some search and uh use the
internet and you could figure out the
answer and then tell me what that answer
is and we can do the exact exact same
thing with these models so think of the
knowledge inside the neural network
inside its billions of parameters think
of that as kind of a vague recollection
of the things that the model has seen
during its training during the
pre-training stage a long time ago so
think of that knowledge in the
parameters as something you read a month
ago and if you keep reading something
then you will remember it and the model
remembers that but if it's something
rare then you probably don't have a
really good recollection of that
information but what you and I do is we
just go and look it up now when you go
and look it up what you're doing
basically is like you're refreshing your
working memory with information and then
you're able to sort of like retrieve it
talk about it or Etc so we need some
equivalent of allowing the model to
refresh its memory or its recollection
and we can do that by introducing tools
uh for the
models so the way we are going to
approach this is that instead of just
saying hey I'm sorry I don't know we can
attempt to use tools so we can create uh
a mechanism
by which the language model can emit
special tokens and these are tokens that
we're going to introduce new tokens so
for example here I've introduced two
tokens and I've introduced a format or a
protocol for how the model is allowed to
use these tokens so for example instead
of answering the question when the model
does not instead of just saying I don't
know sorry the model has the option now
to emitting the special token search
start and this is the query that will go
to like bing.com in the case of openai
or say Google search or something like
that so it will emit the query and then
it will emit search end and then here
what will happen is that the program
that is sampling from the model that is
running the inference when it sees the
special token search end instead of
sampling the next token uh in the
sequence it will actually pause
generating from the model it will go off
it will open a session with bing.com and
it will paste the search query into Bing
and it will then um get all the text
that is retrieved and it will basically
take that text it will maybe represent
it again with some other special tokens
or something like that and it will take
that text and it will copy paste it here
into what I Tred to like show with the
brackets so all that text kind of comes
here and when the text comes here it
enters the context window so the model
so that text from the web search is now
inside the context window that will feed
into the neural network and you should
think of the context window as kind of
like the working memory of the model
that data that is in the context window
is directly accessible by the model it
directly feeds into the neural network
so it's not anymore a vague recollection
it's data that it it has in the context
window and is directly available to that
model so now when it's sampling the new
uh tokens here afterwards it can
reference very easily the data that has
been copy pasted in there so that's
roughly how these um how these tools use
uh tools uh function
and so web search is just one of the
tools we're going to look at some of the
other tools in a bit uh but basically
you introduce new tokens you introduce
some schema by which the model can
utilize these tokens and can call these
special functions like web search
functions and how do you teach the model
how to correctly use these tools like
say web search search start search end
Etc well again you do that through
training sets so we need now to have a
bunch of data and a bunch of
conversations that show the model by
example how to use web search so what
are the what are the settings where you
are using the search um and what does
that look like and here's by example how
you start a search and the search Etc
and uh if you have a few thousand maybe
examples of that in your training set
the model will actually do a pretty good
job of understanding uh how this tool
works and it will know how to sort of
structure its queries and of course
because of the pre-training data set and
its understanding of the world it
actually kind of understands what a web
search is and so it actually kind of has
a pretty good native understanding
um of what kind of stuff is a good
search query um and so it all kind of
just like works you just need a little
bit of a few examples to show it how to
use this new tool and then it can lean
on it to retrieve information and uh put
it in the context window and that's
equivalent to you and I looking
something up because once it's in the
context it's in the working memory and
it's very easy to manipulate and access
so that's what we saw a few minutes ago
when I was searching on chat GPT for who
is Orson kovats the chat GPT language
model decided Ed that this is some kind
of a rare um individual or something
like that and instead of giving me an
answer from its memory it decided that
it will sample a special token that is
going to do web search and we saw
briefly something flash it was like
using the web tool or something like
that so it briefly said that and then we
waited for like two seconds and then it
generated this and you see how it's
creating references here and so it's
citing sources so what happened here is
it went off it did a web web search it
found these sources and these URLs and
the text of these web pages was all
stuffed in between here and it's not
showing here but it's it's basically
stuffed as text in between here and now
it sees that text and now it kind of
references it and says that okay it
could be these people citation could be
those people citation Etc so that's what
happened here and that's what and that's
why when I said who is Orson kovats I
could also say don't use any tools and
then that's enough to um
basically convince chat PT to not use
tools and just use its memory and its
recollection I also went off and I um
tried to ask this question of Chachi PT
so how many standing cups did uh Dominic
Hasek win and Chachi P actually decided
that it knows the answer and it has the
confidence to say that uh he want twice
and so it kind of just relied on its
memory because presumably it has um it
has enough of
a kind of confidence in its weights in
it parameters and activations that this
is uh retrievable just for memory um but
you can also
conversely use web search to make sure
and then for the same query it actually
goes off and it searches and then it
finds a bunch of sources it finds all
this all of this stuff gets copy pasted
in there and then it tells us uh to
again and sites and it actually says the
Wikipedia article which is the source of
this information for us as well so
that's tools web search the model
determines when to search and then uh
that's kind of like how these tools uh
work and this is an additional kind of
mitigation for uh hallucinations and
factuality so I want to stress one more
time this very important sort of
psychology
Point knowledge in the parameters of the
neural network is a vague recollection
the knowledge in the tokens that make up
the context
window is the working memory and it
roughly speaking Works kind of like um
it works for us in our brain the stuff
we remember is our parameters uh and the
stuff that we just experienced like a
few seconds or minutes ago and so on you
can imagine that being in our context
window and this context window is being
built up as you have a conscious
experience around you so this has a
bunch of um implications also for your
use of LOLs in practice so for example I
can go to chat GPT and I can do
something like this I can say can you
Summarize chapter one of Jane Austin's
Pride and Prejudice right and this is a
perfectly fine prompt and Chach actually
does something relatively reasonable
here and but the reason it does that is
because Chach has a pretty good
recollection of a famous work like Pride
and Prejudice it's probably seen a ton
of stuff about it there's probably
forums about this book it's probably
read versions of this book um and it's
kind of like remembers because even if
you've read this or articles about it
you'd kind of have a recollection enough
to actually say all this but usually
when I actually interact with LMS and I
want them to recall specific things it
always works better if you just give it
to them so I think a much better prompt
would be something like this can you
summarize for me chapter one of genos's
spr and Prejudice and then I am
attaching it below for your reference
and then I do something like a delimeter
here and I paste it in and I I found
that just copy pasting it from some
website that I found here um so copy
pasting the chapter one here and I do
that because when it's in the context
window the model has direct access to it
and can exactly it doesn't have to
recall it it just has access to it and
so this summary is can be expected to be
a significantly high quality or higher
quality than this summary uh just
because it's directly available to the
model and I think you and I would work
in the same way if you want to it would
be you would produce a much better
summary if you had reread this chapter
before you had to summarize it and
that's basically what's happening here
or the equivalent of it the next sort of
psychological Quirk I'd like to talk
about briefly is that of the knowledge
of self so what I see very often on the
internet is that people do something
like this they ask llms something like
what model are you and who built you and
um basically this uh question is a
little bit nonsensical and the reason I
say that is that as I try to kind of
explain with some of the underhood
fundamentals this thing is not a person
right it doesn't have a persistent
existence in any way it sort of boots up
processes tokens and shuts off and it
does that for every single person it
just kind of builds up a context window
of conversation and then everything gets
deleted and so this this entity is kind
of like restarted from scratch every
single conversation if that makes sense
it has no persistent self it has no
sense of self it's a token tumbler and
uh it follows the statistical
regularities of its training set so it
doesn't really make sense to ask it who
are you what build you Etc and by
default if you do what I described and
just by default and from nowhere you're
going to get some pretty random answers
so for example let's uh pick on Falcon
which is a fairly old model and let's
see what it tells
us uh so it's evading the question uh
talented engineers and developers here
it says I was built by open AI based on
the gpt3 model it's totally making stuff
up now the fact that it's built by open
AI here I think a lot of people would
take this as evidence that this model
was somehow trained on open AI data or
something like that I don't actually
think that that's necessarily true the
reason for that is
that if you don't explicitly program the
model to answer these kinds of questions
then what you're going to get is its
statistical best guess at the answer and
this model had a um sft data mixture of
conversations and during the
fine-tuning um the model sort of
understands as it's training on this
data that it's taking on this
personality of this like helpful
assistant and it doesn't know how to it
doesn't actually it wasn't told exactly
what label to apply to self it just kind
of is taking on this uh this uh Persona
of a helpful assistant and remember that
the pre-training stage took the
documents from the entire internet and
Chach and open AI are very prominent in
these documents and so I think what's
actually likely to be happening here is
that this is just its hallucinated label
for what it is this is its self-identity
is that it's chat GPT by open Ai and
it's only saying that because there's a
ton of data on the internet of um
answers like this that are actually
coming from open from chasht and So
that's its label for what it is now you
can override this as a developer if you
have a llm model you can actually
override it and there are a few ways to
do that so for example let me show you
there's this MMO model from Allen Ai and
um this is one llm it's not a top tier
LM or anything like that but I like it
because it is fully open source so the
paper for Almo and everything else is
completely fully open source which is
nice um so here we are looking at its
sft mixture so this is the data mixture
of um the fine tuning so this is the
conversations data it right and so the
way that they are solving it for Theo
model is we see that there's a bunch of
stuff in the mixture and there's a total
of 1 million conversations here but here
we have alot to hardcoded if we go there
we see that this is 240
conversations and look at these 240
conversations they're hardcoded tell me
about yourself says user and then the
assistant says I'm and open language
model developed by AI to Allen Institute
of artificial intelligence Etc I'm here
to help blah blah blah what is your name
uh Theo project so these are all kinds
of like cooked up hardcoded questions
abouto 2 and the correct answers to give
in these cases if you take 240 questions
like this or conversations put them into
your training set and fine tune with it
then the model will actually be expected
to parot this stuff later if you don't
give it this then it's probably a Chach
by open
Ai and um there's one more way to
sometimes do this is
that basically um in these conversations
and you have terms between human and
assistant sometimes there's a special
message called system message at the
very beginning of the conversation so
it's not just between human and
assistant there's a system and in the
system message you can actually hardcode
and remind the model that hey you are a
model developed by open Ai and your name
is chashi pt40 and you were trained on
this date and your knowledge cut off is
this and basically it kind of like
documents the model a little bit and
then this is inserted into to your
conversations so when you go on chpt you
see a blank page but actually the system
message is kind of like hidden in there
and those tokens are in the context
window and so those are the two ways to
kind of um program the models to talk
about themselves either it's done
through uh data like this or it's done
through system message and things like
that basically invisible tokens that are
in the context window and remind the
model of its identity but it's all just
kind of like cooked up and bolted on in
some in some way it's not actually like
really deeply there in any real sense as
it would before a human I want to now
continue to the next section which deals
with the computational capabilities or
like I should say the native
computational capabilities of these
models in problem solving scenarios and
so in particular we have to be very
careful with these models when we
construct our examples of conversations
and there's a lot of sharp edges here
that are kind of like elucidative is
that a word uh they're kind of like
interesting to look at when we consider
how these models think so um consider
the following prompt from a human and
supposed that basically that we are
building out a conversation to enter
into our training set of conversations
so we're going to train the model on
this we're teaching you how to basically
solve simple math problems so the prompt
is Emily buys three apples and two
oranges each orange cost $2 the total
cost is 13 what is the cost of apples
very simple math question now there are
two answers here on the left and on the
right they are both correct answers they
both say that the answer is three which
is correct but one of these two is a
significant ific anly better answer for
the assistant than the other like if I
was Data labeler and I was creating one
of these one of these would be uh a
really terrible answer for the assistant
and the other would be okay and so I'd
like you to potentially pause the video
Even and think through why one of these
two is significantly better answer uh
than the other and um if you use the
wrong one your model will actually be uh
really bad at math potentially and it
would have uh bad outcomes and this is
something that you would be careful with
in your life labeling documentations
when you are training people uh to
create the ideal responses for the
assistant okay so the key to this
question is to realize and remember that
when the models are training and also
inferencing they are working in
onedimensional sequence of tokens from
left to right and this is the picture
that I often have in my mind I imagine
basically the token sequence evolving
from left to right and to always produce
the next token in a sequence we are
feeding all these tokens into the neural
network and this neural network then is
the probabilities for the next token and
sequence right so this picture here is
the exact same picture we saw uh before
up here and this comes from the web demo
that I showed you before right so this
is the calculation that basically takes
the input tokens here on the top and uh
performs these operations of all these
neurons and uh gives you the answer for
the probabilities of what comes next now
the important thing to realize is that
roughly
speaking uh there's basically a finite
number of layers of computation that
happened here so for example this model
here has only one two three layers of
what's called detention and uh MLP here
um maybe um typical modern
state-of-the-art Network would have more
like say 100 layers or something like
that but there's only 100 layers of
computation or something like that to go
from the previous token sequence to the
probabilities for the next token and so
there's a finite amount of computation
that happens here for every single token
and you should think of this as a very
small amount of computation and this
amount of computation is almost roughly
fixed uh for every single token in this
sequence um the that's not actually
fully true because the more tokens you
feed in uh the the more expensive uh
this forward pass will be of this neural
network but not by much so you should
think of this uh and I think as a good
model to have in mind this is a fixed
amount of compute that's going to happen
in this box for every single one of
these tokens and this amount of compute
Cann possibly be too big because there's
not that many layers that are sort of
going from the top to bottom here
there's not that that much
computationally that will happen here
and so you can't imagine the model to to
basically do arbitrary computation in a
single forward pass to get a single
token and so what that means is that we
actually have to distribute our
reasoning and our computation across
many tokens because every single token
is only spending a finite amount of
computation on it and so we kind of want
to distribute the computation across
many tokens and we can't have too much
computation or expect too much
computation out of of the model in any
single individual token because there's
only so much computation that happens
per token okay roughly fixed amount of
computation here
so that's why this answer here is
significantly worse and the reason for
that is Imagine going from left to right
here um and I copy pasted it right here
the answer is three Etc imagine the
model having to go from left to right
emitting these tokens one at a time it
has to say or we're expecting to say the
answer is space dollar sign and then
right here we're expecting it to
basically cram all of the computation of
this problem into this single token it
has to emit the correct answer three and
then once we've emitted the answer three
we're expecting it to say all these
tokens but at this point we've already
prod produced the answer and it's
already in the context window for all
these tokens that follow so anything
here is just um kind of post Hawk
justification of why this is the answer
um because the answer is already created
it's already in the token window so it's
it's not actually being calculated here
um and so if you are answering the
question directly and immediately you
are training the model to to try to
basically guess the answer in a single
token and that is just not going to work
because of the finite amount of
computation that happens per token
that's why this answer on the right is
significantly better because we are
Distributing this computation across the
answer we're actually getting the model
to sort of slowly come to the answer
from the left to right we're getting
intermediate results we're saying okay
the total cost of oranges is four so 30
- 4 is 9 and so we're creating
intermediate calculations and each one
of these calculations is by itself not
that expensive and so we're actually
basically kind of guessing a little bit
the difficulty that the model is capable
of in any single one of these individual
tokens and there can never be too much
work in any one of these tokens
computationally because then the model
won't be able to do that later at test
time and so we're teaching the model
here to spread out its reasoning and to
spread out its computation over the
tokens and in this way it only has very
simple problems in each token and they
can add up and then by the time it's
near the end it has all the previous
results in its working memory and it's
much easier for it to determine that the
answer is and here it is three so this
is a significantly better label for our
computation this would be really bad and
is teaching the model to try to do all
the computation in a single token and
it's really
bad so uh that's kind of like an
interesting thing to keep in mind is in
your
prompts uh usually don't have to think
about it explicitly because uh the
people at open AI have labelers and so
on that actually worry about this and
they make sure that the answers are
spread out and so actually open AI will
kind of like do the right thing so when
I ask this question for chat GPT it's
actually going to go very slowly it's
going to be like okay let's define our
variables set up the equation
and it's kind of creating all these
intermediate results these are not for
you these are for the model if the model
is not creating these intermediate
results for itself it's not going to be
able to reach three I also wanted to
show you that it's possible to be a bit
mean to the model uh we can just ask for
things so as an example I said I gave it
the exact same uh prompt and I said
answer the question in a single token
just immediately give me the answer
nothing else and it turns out that for
this simple um prompt here it actually
was able to do it in single go so it
just created a single I think this is
two tokens right uh because the dollar
sign is its own token so basically this
model didn't give me a single token it
gave me two tokens but it still produced
the correct answer and it did that in a
single forward pass of the
network now that's because the numbers
here I think are very simple and so I
made it a bit more difficult to be a bit
mean to the model so I said Emily buys
23 apples and 177 oranges and then I
just made the numbers a bit bigger and
I'm just making it harder for the model
I'm asking it to more computation in a
single token and so I said the same
thing and here it gave me five and five
is actually not correct so the model
failed to do all of this calculation in
a single forward pass of the network it
failed to go from the input tokens and
then in a single forward pass of the
network single go through the network it
couldn't produce the result and then I
said okay now don't worry about the the
token limit and just solve the problem
as usual and then it goes all the
intermediate results it simplifies and
every one of these intermediate results
here and intermediate calculations is
much easier for the model and um it sort
of it's not too much work per token all
of the tokens here are correct and it
arises the solution which is seven and I
just couldn't squeeze all of this work
it couldn't squeeze that into a single
forward passive Network so I think
that's kind of just a cute example and
something to kind of like think about
and I think it's kind of again just
elucidative in terms of how these uh
models work the last thing that I would
say on this topic is that if I was in
practi is trying to actually solve this
in my day-to-day life I might actually
not uh trust that the model that all the
intermediate calculations correctly here
so actually probably what I do is
something like this I would come here
and I would say use code and uh that's
because code is one of the possible
tools that chachy PD can use and instead
of it having to do mental arithmetic
like this mental arithmetic here I don't
fully trust it and especially if the
numbers get really big there's no
guarantee that the model will do this
correctly any one of these intermediates
steps might in principle fail we're
using neural networks to do mental
arithmetic uh kind of like you doing
mental arithmetic in your brain it might
just like uh screw up some of the
intermediate results it's actually kind
of amazing that it can even do this kind
of mental arithmetic I don't think I
could do this in my head but basically
the model is kind of like doing it in
its head and I don't trust that so I
wanted to use tools so you can say stuff
like use
code and uh I'm not sure what happened
there use
code and so um like I mentioned there's
a special tool and the uh the model can
write code and I can inspect that this
code is correct and then uh it's not
relying on its mental arithmetic it is
using the python interpreter which is a
very simple programming language to
basically uh write out the code that
calculates the result and I would
personally trust this a lot more because
this came out of a Python program which
I think has a lot more correctness
guarantees than the mental arithmetic of
a language model uh so just um another
kind of uh potential hint that if you
have these kinds of problems uh you may
want to basically just uh ask the model
to use the code interpreter and just
like we saw with the web search the
model has special uh kind of tokens for
calling uh like it will not actually
generate these tokens from the language
model it will write the program and then
it actually sends that program to a
different sort of part of the computer
that actually just runs that program and
brings back the result and then the
model gets access to that result and can
tell you that okay the cost of each
apple is seven
um so that's another kind of tool and I
would use this in practice for yourself
and it's um yeah it's just uh less error
prone I would say so that's why I called
this section models need tokens to think
distribute your competition across many
tokens ask models to create intermediate
results or whenever you can lean on
tools and Tool use instead of allowing
the models to do all of the stuff in
their memory so if they try to do it all
in their memory I don't fully trust it
and prefer to use tools whenever
possible I want to show you one more
example of where this actually comes up
and that's in counting so models
actually are not very good at counting
for the exact same reason you're asking
for way too much in a single individual
token so let me show you a simple
example of that um how many dots are
below and then I just put in a bunch of
dots and Chach says there are and then
it just tries to solve the problem in a
single token so in a single token it has
to count the number of dots in its
context window
um and it has to do that in the single
forward pass of a network and a single
forward pass of a network as we talked
about there's not that much computation
that can happen there just think of that
as being like very little competation
that happens there so if I just look at
what the model sees let's go to the LM
go to tokenizer it sees uh
this how many dots are below and then it
turns out that these dots here this
group of I think 20 dots is a single
token and then this group of whatever it
is is another token and then for some
reason they break up as this so I don't
actually this has to do with the details
of the tokenizer but it turns out that
these um the model basically sees the
token ID this this this and so on and
then from these token IDs it's expected
to count the number and spoiler alert is
not 161 it's actually I believe
177 so here's what we can do instead uh
we can say use code and you might expect
that like why should this work and it's
actually kind of subtle and kind of
interesting so when I say use code I
actually expect this to work let's see
okay 177 is correct so what happens here
is I've actually it doesn't look like it
but I've broken down the problem into a
problems that are easier for the model I
know that the model can't count it can't
do mental counting but I know that the
model is actually pretty good at doing
copy pasting so what I'm doing here is
when I say use code it creates a string
in Python for this and the task of
basically copy pasting my input here to
here is very simple because for the
model um it sees this string of uh it
sees it as just these four tokens or
whatever it is so it's very simple for
the model to copy paste those token IDs
and um kind of unpack them into Dots
here and so it creates this string and
then it calls python routine. count and
then it comes up with the correct answer
so the python interpreter is doing the
counting it's not the models mental
arithmetic doing the counting so it's
again a simple example of um models need
tokens to think don't rely on their
mental arithmetic and um that's why also
the models are not very good at counting
if you need them to do counting tasks
always ask them to lean on the tool now
the models also have many other little
cognitive deficits here and there and
these are kind of like sharp edges of
the technology to be kind of aware of
over time so as an example the models
are not very good with all kinds of
spelling related tasks they're not very
good at it and I told you that we would
loop back around to tokenization and the
reason to do for this is that the models
they don't see the characters they see
tokens and they their entire world is
about tokens which are these little text
chunks and so they don't see characters
like our eyes do and so very simple
character level tasks often fail so for
example uh I'm giving it a string
ubiquitous and I'm asking it to print
only every third character starting with
the first one so we start with U and
then we should go every third so every
so 1 2 3 Q should be next and then Etc
so this I see is not correct and again
my hypothesis is that this is again
Dental arithmetic here is failing number
one a little bit but number two I think
the the more important issue here is
that if you go to Tik
tokenizer and you look at ubiquitous we
see that it is three tokens right so you
and I see ubiquitous and we can easily
access the individual letters because we
kind of see them and when we have it in
the working memory of our visual sort of
field we can really easily index into
every third letter and I can do that
task but the models don't have access to
the individual letters they see this as
these three tokens and uh remember these
models are trained from scratch on the
internet and all these token uh
basically the model has to discover how
many of all these different letters are
packed into all these different tokens
and the reason we even use tokens is
mostly for efficiency uh but I think a
lot of people areed interested to delete
tokens entirely like we should really
have character level or bite level
models it's just that that would create
very long sequences and people don't
know how to deal with that right now so
while we have the token World any kind
of spelling tasks are not actually
expected to work super well so because I
know that spelling is not a strong suit
because of tokenization I can again Ask
it to lean On Tools so I can just say
use code and I would again expect this
to work because the task of copy pasting
ubiquitous into the python interpreter
is much easier and then we're leaning on
python interpreter to manipulate the
characters of this string so when I say
use
code
ubiquitous yes it indexes into every
third character and the actual truth is
u2s
uqs uh which looks correct to me so um
again an example of spelling related
tasks not working very well a very
famous example of that recently is how
many R are there in strawberry and this
went viral many times and basically the
models now get it correct they say there
are three Rs in Strawberry but for a
very long time all the state-of-the-art
models would insist that there are only
two RS in strawberry and this caused a
lot of you know Ruckus because is that a
word I think so because um it just kind
of like why are the models so brilliant
and they can solve math Olympiad
questions but they can't like count RS
in strawberry and the answer for that
again is I've got built up to it kind of
slowly but number one the models don't
see characters they see tokens and
number two they are not very good at
counting and so here we are combining
the difficulty of seeing the characters
with the difficulty of counting and
that's why the models struggled with
this even though I think by now honestly
I think open I may have hardcoded the
answer here or I'm not sure what they
did but um uh but this specific query
now works
so models are not very good at spelling
and there there's a bunch of other
little sharp edges and I don't want to
go into all of them I just want to show
you a few examples of things to be aware
of and uh when you're using these models
in practice I don't actually want to
have a comprehensive analysis here of
all the ways that the models are kind of
like falling short I just want to make
the point that there are some Jagged
edges here and there and we've discussed
a few of them and a few of them make
sense but some of them also will just
not make as much sense and they're kind
of like you're left scratching your head
even if you understand in- depth how
these models work and and good example
of that recently is the following uh the
models are not very good at very simple
questions like this and uh this is
shocking to a lot of people because
these math uh these problems can solve
complex math problems they can answer
PhD grade physics chemistry biology
questions much better than I can but
sometimes they fall short in like super
simple problems like this so here we go
9.11 is bigger than 9.9 and it justifies
it in some way but obviously and then at
the end okay it actually it flips its
decision later so um I don't believe
that this is very reproducible sometimes
it flips around its answer sometimes
gets it right sometimes get it get it
wrong uh let's try
again okay even though it might look
larger okay so here it doesn't even
correct itself in the end if you ask
many times sometimes it gets it right
too but how is it that the model can do
so great at Olympiad grade problems but
then fail on very simple problems like
this and uh I think this one is as I
mentioned a little bit of a head
scratcher it turns out that a bunch of
people studied this in depth and I
haven't actually read the paper uh but
what I was told by this team was that
when you scrutinize the activations
inside the neural network when you look
at some of the features and what what
features turn on or off and what neurons
turn on or off uh a bunch of neurons
inside the neural network light up that
are usually associated with Bible verses
U and so I think the model is kind of
like reminded that these almost look
like Bible verse markers and in a bip
verse setting 9.11 would come after 99.9
and so basically the model somehow finds
it like cognitively very distracting
that in Bible verses 9.11 would be
greater um even though here it's
actually trying to justify it and come
up to the answer with a math it still
ends up with the wrong answer here so it
basically just doesn't fully make sense
and it's not fully understood and um
there's a few Jagged issues like that so
that's why treat this as a as what it is
which is a St stochastic system that is
really magical but that you can't also
fully trust and you want to use it as a
tool not as something that you kind of
like letter rip on a problem and
copypaste the results okay so we have
now covered two major stages of training
of large language models we saw that in
the first stage this is called the
pre-training stage we are basically
training on internet documents and when
you train a language model on internet
documents you get what's called a base
model and it's basically an internet
document simulator right now we saw that
this is an interesting artifact and uh
this takes many months to train on
thousands of computers and it's kind of
a lossy compression of the internet and
it's extremely interesting but it's not
directly useful because we don't want to
sample internet documents we want to ask
questions of an AI and have it respond
to our questions so for that we need an
assistant and we saw that we can
actually construct an assistant in the
process of a post
training and specifically in the process
of supervised fine-tuning as we call
it so in this stage we saw that it's
algorithmically identical to
pre-training nothing is going to change
the only thing that changes is the data
set so instead of Internet documents we
now want to create and curate a very
nice data set of conversations so we
want Millions conversations on all kinds
of diverse topics between a human and an
assistant and fundamentally these
conversations are created by humans so
humans write the prompts and humans
write the ideal response responses and
they do that based on labeling
documentations now in the modern stack
it's not actually done fully and
manually by humans right they actually
now have a lot of help from these tools
so we can use language models um to help
us create these data sets and that's
done extensively but fundamentally it's
all still coming from Human curation at
the end so we create these conversations
that now becomes our data set we fine
tune on it or continue training on it
and we get an assistant and then we kind
of shifted gears and started talking
about some of the kind of cognitive
implications of what this assistant is
like and we saw that for example the
assistant will hallucinate if you don't
take some sort of mitigations towards it
so we saw that hallucinations would be
common and then we looked at some of the
mitigations of those hallucinations and
then we saw that the models are quite
impressive and can do a lot of stuff in
their head but we saw that they can also
Lean On Tools to become better so for
example we can lo lean on a web search
in order to hallucinate less and to
maybe bring up some more um recent
information or something like that or we
can lean on tools like code interpreter
so the code can so the llm can write
some code and actually run it and see
the
results so these are some of the topics
we looked at so far um now what I'd like
to do is I'd like to cover the last and
major stage of this Pipeline and that is
reinforcement learning so reinforcement
learning is still kind of thought to be
under the umbrella of posttraining uh
but it is the last third major stage and
it's a different way of training
language models and usually follows as
this third step so inside companies like
open AI you will start here and these
are all separate teams so there's a team
doing data for pre-training and a team
doing training for pre-training and then
there's a team doing all the
conversation generation in a in a
different team that is kind of doing the
supervis fine tuning and there will be a
team for the reinforcement learning as
well so it's kind of like a handoff of
these models you get your base model the
then you find you need to be an
assistant and then you go into
reinforcement learning which we'll talk
about uh
now so that's kind of like the major
flow and so let's now focus on
reinforcement learning the last major
stage of training and let me first
actually motivate it and why we would
want to do reinforcement learning and
what it looks like on a high level so I
would now like to try to motivate the
reinforcement learning stage and what it
corresponds to with something that
you're probably familiar with and that
is basically going to school so just
like you went to school to become um
really good at something we want to take
large language models through school and
really what we're doing is um we're um
we have a few paradigms of ways of uh
giving them knowledge or transferring
skills so in particular when we're
working with textbooks in school you'll
see that there are three major kind of
uh pieces of information in these
textbooks three classes of information
the first thing you'll see is you'll see
a lot of exposition um and by the way
this is a totally random book I pulled
from the internet I I think it's some
kind of an organic chemistry or
something I'm not sure uh but the
important thing is that you'll see that
most of the text most of it is kind of
just like the meat of it is exposition
it's kind of like background knowledge
Etc as you are reading through the words
of this Exposition you can think of that
roughly as training on that data so um
and that's why when you're reading
through this stuff this background
knowledge and this all this context
information it's kind of equivalent to
pre-training so it's it's where we build
sort of like a knowledge base of this
data and get a sense of the topic the
next major kind of information that you
will see is these uh problems and with
their worked Solutions so basically a
human expert in this case uh the author
of this book has given us not just a
problem but has also worked through the
solution and the solution is basically
like equivalent to having like this
ideal response for an assistant so it's
basically the expert is showing us how
to solve the problem in it's uh kind of
like um in its full form so as we are
reading the solution we are basically
training on the expert data and then
later we can try to imitate the expert
um and basically um that's that roughly
correspond to having the sft model
that's what it would be doing so
basically we've already done
pre-training and we've already covered
this um imitation of experts and how
they solve these problems and the third
stage of reinforcement learning is
basically the practice problems so
sometimes you'll see this is just a
single practice problem here but of
course there will be usually many
practice problems at the end of each
chapter in any textbook and practice
problems of course we know are critical
for learning because what are they
getting you to do they're getting you to
practice uh to practice yourself and
discover ways of solving these problems
yourself and so what you get in a
practice problem is you get a problem
description but you're not given the
solution but you are given the final
answer answer usually in the answer key
of the textbook and so you know the
final answer that you're trying to get
to and you have the problem statement
but you don't have the solution you are
trying to practice the solution you're
trying out many different things and
you're seeing what gets you to the final
solution the best and so you're
discovering how to solve these problems
so and in the process of that you're
relying on number one the background
information which comes from
pre-training and number two maybe a
little bit of imitation of human experts
and you can probably try similar kinds
of solutions and so on so we've done
this and this and now in this section
we're going to try to practice and so
we're going to be given prompts we're
going to be given Solutions U sorry the
final answers but we're not going to be
given expert Solutions we have to
practice and try stuff out and that's
what reinforcement learning is about
okay so let's go back to the problem
that we worked with previously just so
we have a concrete example to talk
through as we explore sort of the topic
here so um I'm here in the Teck
tokenizer because I'd also like to well
I get a text box which is useful but
number two I want to remind you again
that we're always working with
onedimensional token sequences and so um
I actually like prefer this view because
this is like the native view of the llm
if that makes sense like this is what it
actually sees it sees token IDs right
okay so Emily buys three apples and two
oranges each orange is $2 the total cost
of all the fruit is $13 what is the cost
of each apple
and what I'd like to what I like you to
appreciate here is these are like four
possible candidate Solutions as an
example and they all reach the answer
three now what I'd like you to
appreciate at this point is that if I am
the human data labeler that is creating
a conversation to be entered into the
training set I don't actually really
know which of these
conversations to um to add to the data
set some of these conversations kind of
set up a system equations some of them
sort of like just talk through it in
English and some of them just kind of
like skip right through to the
solution um if you look at chbt for
example and you give it this question it
defines a system of variables and it
kind of like does this little thing what
we have to appreciate and uh
differentiate between though is um the
first purpose of a solution is to reach
the right answer of course we want to
get the final answer three that is the
that is the important purpose here but
there's kind of like a secondary purpose
as well where here we are also just kind
of trying to make it like nice uh for
the human because we're kind of assuming
that the person wants to see the
solution they want to see the
intermediate steps we want to present it
nicely Etc so there are two separate
things going on here number one is the
presentation for the human but number
two we're trying to actually get the
right answer um so let's for the moment
focus on just reaching the final answer
if we're only care if we only care about
the final answer then which of these is
the optimal or the best prompt um sorry
the best solution for the llm to reach
the right
answer um and what I'm trying to get at
is we don't know me as a human labeler I
would not know which one of these is
best so as an example we saw earlier on
when we looked at
um the token sequences here and the
mental arithmetic and reasoning we saw
that for each token we can only spend
basically a finite number of finite
amount of compute here that is not very
large or you should think about it that
way way and so we can't actually make
too big of a leap in any one token is is
maybe the way to think about it so as an
example in this one what's really nice
about it is that it's very few tokens so
it's going to take us very short amount
of time to get to the answer but right
here when we're doing 30 - 4 IDE 3
equals right in this token here we're
actually asking for a lot of computation
to happen on that single individual
token and so maybe this is a bad example
to give to the llm because it's kind of
incentivizing it to skip through the
calculations very quickly and it's going
to actually make up mistakes make
mistakes in this mental arithmetic uh so
maybe it would work better to like
spread out the spread it out more maybe
it would be better to set it up as an
equation maybe it would be better to
talk through it we fundamentally don't
know and we don't know because what is
easy for you or I as or as human
labelers what's easy for us or hard for
us is different than what's easy or hard
for the llm it cognition is different um
and the token sequences are kind of like
different hard for it and so some of the
token sequences here that are trivial
for me might be um very too much of a
leap for the llm so right here this
token would be way too hard but
conversely many of the tokens that I'm
creating here might be just trivial to
the llm and we're just wasting tokens
like why waste all these tokens when
this is all trivial so if the only thing
we care care about is the final answer
and we're separating out the issue of
the presentation to the human um then we
don't actually really know how to
annotate this example we don't know what
solution to get to the llm because we
are not the
llm and it's clear here in the case of
like the math example but this is
actually like a very pervasive issue
like for our knowledge is not lm's
knowledge like the llm actually has a
ton of knowledge of PhD in math and
physics chemistry and whatnot so in many
ways it actually knows more than I do
and I'm I'm potentially not utilizing
that knowledge in its problem solving
but conversely I might be injecting a
bunch of knowledge in my solutions that
the LM doesn't know in its parameters
and then those are like sudden leaps
that are very confusing to the model and
so our cognitions are different and I
don't really know what to put here if
all we care about is the reaching the
final solution and doing it economically
ideally and so long story short we are
not in a good position to create these
uh token sequences for the LM and
they're useful by imitation to
initialize the system but we really want
the llm to discover the token sequences
that work for it we need to find it
needs to find for itself what token
sequence reliably gets to the answer
given the prompt and it needs to
discover that in the process of
reinforcement learning and of trial and
error so let's see how this example
would work like in reinforcement
learning
okay so we're now back in the huging
face inference playground and uh that
just allows me to very easily call uh
different kinds of models so as an
example here on the top right I chose
the Gemma 2 2 billion parameter model so
two billion is very very small so this
is a tiny model but it's okay so we're
going to give it um the way that
reinforcement learning will basically
work is actually quite quite simple um
we need to try many different kinds of
solutions and we want to see which
Solutions work well or not
so we're basically going to take the
prompt we're going to run the
model and the model generates a solution
and then we're going to inspect the
solution and we know that the correct
answer for this one is $3 and so indeed
the model gets it correct it says it's
$3 so this is correct so that's just one
attempt at DIS solution so now we're
going to delete this and we're going to
rerun it again let's try a second
attempt so the model solves it in a bit
slightly different way right every
single attempt will be a different
generation because these models are
stochastic systems remember that at
every single token here we have a
probability distribution and we're
sampling from that distribution so we
end up kind kind of going down slightly
different paths and so this is a second
solution that also ends in the correct
answer now we're going to delete that
let's go a third
time okay so again slightly different
solution but also gets it
correct now we can actually repeat this
uh many times and so in practice you
might actually sample thousand of
independent Solutions or even like
million solutions for just a single
prompt um and some of them will be
correct and some of them will not be
very correct and basically what we want
to do is we want to encourage the
solutions that lead to correct answers
so let's take a look at what that looks
like so if we come back over here here's
kind of like a cartoon diagram of what
this is looking like we have a prompt
and then we tried many different
solutions in
parallel and some of the solutions um
might go well so they get the right
answer which is in green and some of the
solutions might go poorly and may not
reach the right answer which is red now
this problem here unfortunately is not
the best example because it's a trivial
prompt and as we saw uh even like a two
billion parameter model always gets it
right so it's not the best example in
that sense but let's just exercise some
imagination here and let's just suppose
that the um green ones are good and the
red ones are
bad okay so we generated 15 Solutions
only four of them got the right answer
and so now what we want to do is
basically we want to encourage the kinds
of solutions that lead to right answers
so whatever token sequences happened in
these red Solutions obviously something
went wrong along the way somewhere and
uh this was not a good path to take
through the solution and whatever token
sequences there were in these Green
Solutions well things went uh pretty
well in this situation and so we want to
do more things like it in prompts like
this and the way we encourage this kind
of a behavior in the future is we
basically train on these sequences um
but these training sequencies now are
not coming from expert human annotators
there's no human who decided that this
is the correct solution this solution
came from the model itself so the model
is practicing here it's tried out a few
Solutions four of them seem to have
worked and now the model will kind of
like train on them and this corresponds
to a student basically looking at their
Solutions and being like okay well this
one worked really well so this is this
is how I should be solving these kinds
of problems and uh here in this example
there are many different ways to
actually like really tweak the
methodology a little bit here but just
to give the core idea across maybe it's
simplest to just think about take the
taking the single best solution out of
these four uh like say this one that's
why it was yellow uh so this is the the
solution that not only led to the right
answer but may maybe had some other nice
properties maybe it was the shortest one
or it looked nicest in some ways or uh
there's other criteria you could think
of as an example but we're going to
decide that this the top solution we're
going to train on it and then uh the
model will be slightly more likely once
you do the parameter update to take this
path in this kind of a setting in the
future but you have to remember that
we're going to run many different
diverse prompts across lots of math
problems and physics problems and
whatever wherever there might be so tens
of thousands of prompts maybe have in
mind there's thousands of solutions
prompt and so this is all happening kind
of like at the same time and as we're
iterating this process the model is
discovering for itself what kinds of
token sequences lead it to correct
answers it's not coming from a human
annotator the the model is kind of like
playing in this playground and it knows
what it's trying to get to and it's
discovering sequences that work for it
uh these are sequences that don't make
any mental leaps uh they they seem to
work reliably and statistically and uh
fully utilize the knowledge of the model
as it has it and so uh this is the
process of reinforcement
learning it's basically a guess and
check we're going to guess many
different types of solutions we're going
to check them and we're going to do more
of what worked in the future and that is
uh reinforcement learning so in the
context of what came before we see now
that the sft model the supervised fine
tuning model it's still helpful because
it still kind of like initializes the
model a little bit into to the vicinity
of the correct Solutions so it's kind of
like a initialization of um of the model
in the sense that it kind of gets the
model to you know take Solutions like
write out Solutions and maybe it has an
understanding of setting up a system of
equations or maybe it kind of like talks
through a solution so it gets you into
the vicinity of correct Solutions but
reinforcement learning is where
everything gets dialed in we really
discover the solutions that work for the
model get the right answers we encourage
them and then the model just kind of
like gets better over time time okay so
that is the high Lev process for how we
train large language models in short we
train them kind of very similar to how
we train children and basically the only
difference is that children go through
chapters of books and they do all these
different types of training exercises um
kind of within the chapter of each book
but instead when we train AIS it's
almost like we kind of do it stage by
stage depending on the type of that
stage so first what we do is we do
pre-training which as we saw is
equivalent to uh basically reading all
the expository material so we look at
all the textbooks at the same time and
we read all the exposition and we try to
build a knowledge base the second thing
then is we go into the sft stage which
is really looking at all the fixed uh
sort of like solutions from Human
Experts of all the different kinds of
worked Solutions across all the
textbooks and we just kind of get an sft
model which is able to imitate the
experts but does so kind of blindly it
just kind of like does its best guess
uh kind of just like trying to mimic
statistically the expert behavior and so
that's what you get when you look at all
the work Solutions and then finally in
the last stage we do all the practice
problems in the RL stage across all the
textbooks we only do the practice
problems and that's how we get the RL
model so on a high level the way we
train llms is very much equivalent uh to
the process that we train uh that we use
for training of children the next point
I would like to make is that actually
these first two stat ages pre-training
and surprise fine-tuning they've been
around for years and they are very
standard and everyone does them all the
different llm providers it is this last
stage the RL training that is a lot more
early in its process of development and
is not standard yet in the field and so
um this stage is a lot more kind of
early and nent and the reason for that
is because I actually skipped over a ton
of little details here in this process
the high level idea is very simple it's
trial and there learning but there's a
ton of details and little math
mathematical kind of like nuances to
exactly how you pick the solutions that
are the best and how much you train on
them and what is the prompt distribution
and how to set up the training run such
that this actually works so there's a
lot of little details and knobs to the
core idea that is very very simple and
so getting the details right here uh is
not trivial and so a lot of companies
like for example open and other LM
providers have experimented internally
with reinforcement learning fine tuning
for llms for a while but they've not
talked about it publicly
um it's all kind of done inside the
company and so that's why the paper from
Deep seek that came out very very
recently was such a big deal because
this is a paper from this company called
DC Kai in China and this paper really
talked very publicly about reinforcement
learning fine training for large
language models and how incredibly
important it is for large language
models and how it brings out a lot of
reasoning capabilities in the models
we'll go into this in a second so this
paper reinvigorated the public interest
of using RL for llms and gave a lot of
the um sort of n-r details that are
needed to reproduce their results and
actually get the stage to work for large
langage models so let me take you
briefly through this uh deep seek R1
paper and what happens when you actually
correctly apply RL to language models
and what that looks like and what that
gives you so the first thing I'll scroll
to is this uh kind of figure two here
where we are looking at the Improvement
in how the models are solving
mathematical problems so this is the
accuracy of solving mathematical
problems on the a accuracy and then we
can go to the web page and we can see
the kinds of problems that are actually
in these um these the kinds of math
problems that are being measured here so
these are simple math problems you can
um pause the video if you like but these
are the kinds of problems that basically
the models are being asked to solve and
you can see that in the beginning
they're not doing very well but then as
you update the model with this many
thousands of steps their accuracy kind
of continues to climb so the models are
improving and they're solving these
problems with a higher accuracy
as you do this trial and error on a
large data set of these kinds of
problems and the models are discovering
how to solve math problems but even more
incredible than the quantitative kind of
results of solving these problems with a
higher accuracy is the qualitative means
by which the model achieves these
results so when we scroll down uh one of
the figures here that is kind of
interesting is that later on in the
optimization the model seems to be uh
using average length per response uh
goes up up so the model seems to be
using more tokens to get its higher
accuracy results so it's learning to
create very very long Solutions why are
these Solutions very long we can look at
them qualitatively here so basically
what they discover is that the model
solution get very very long partially
because so here's a question and here's
kind of the answer from the model what
the model learns to do um and this is an
immerging property of new optimization
it just discovers that this is good for
problem solving is it starts to do stuff
like this wait wait wait that's Nota
moment I can flag here let's reevaluate
this step by step to identify the
correct sum can be so what is the model
doing here right the model is basically
re-evaluating steps it has learned that
it works better for accuracy to try out
lots of ideas try something from
different perspectives retrace reframe
backtrack is doing a lot of the things
that you and I are doing in the process
of problem solving for mathematical
questions but it's rediscovering what
happens in your head not what you put
down on the solution and there is no
human who can hardcode this stuff in the
ideal assistant response this is only
something that can be discovered in the
process of reinforcement learning
because you wouldn't know what to put
here this just turns out to work for the
model and it improves its accuracy in
problem solving so the model learns what
we call these chains of thought in your
head and it's an emergent property of
the optim of the optimization and that's
what's bloating up the response length
but that's also what's increasing the
accuracy of the problem problem solving
so what's incredible here is basically
the model is discovering ways to think
it's learning what I like to call
cognitive strategies of how you
manipulate a problem and how you
approach it from different perspectives
how you pull in some analogies or do
different kinds of things like that and
how you kind of uh try out many
different things over time uh check a
result from different perspectives and
how you kind of uh solve problems but
here it's kind of discovered by the RL
so extremely incredible to see this
emerge in the optimization without
having to hardcode it anywhere the only
thing we've given it are the correct
answers and this comes out from trying
to just solve them correctly which is
incredible
um now let's go back to actually the
problem that we've been working with and
let's take a look at what it would look
like uh for uh for this kind of a model
what we call reasoning or thinking model
to solve that problem okay so recall
that this is the problem we've been
working with and when I pasted it into
chat GPT 40 I'm getting this kind of a
response let's take a look at what
happens when you give this same query to
what's called a reasoning or a thinking
model this is a model that was trained
with reinforcement learning so this
model described in this paper DC car1 is
available on chat. dec.com uh so this is
kind of like the company uh that
developed is hosting it you have to make
sure that the Deep think button is
turned on to get the R1 model as it's
called we can paste it here and run
it and so let's take a look at what
happens now and what is the output of
the model okay so here's it says so this
is previously what we get using
basically what's an sft approach a
supervised funing approach this is like
mimicking an expert solution this is
what we get from the RL model okay let
me try to figure this out so Emily buys
three apples and two oranges each orange
cost $2 total is 13 I need to find out
blah blah blah so here you you um as
you're reading this you can't escape
thinking that this model is
thinking um is definitely pursuing the
solution solution it deres that it must
cost $3 and then it says wait a second
let me check my math again to be sure
and then it tries it from a slightly
different perspective and then it says
yep all that checks out I think that's
the answer I don't see any mistakes let
me see if there's another way to
approach the problem maybe setting up an
equation let's let the cost of one apple
be $8 then blah blah blah yep same
answer so definitely each apple is $3
all right confident that that's correct
and then what it does once it sort of um
did the thinking process is it writes up
the nice solution for the human and so
this is now considering so this is more
about the correctness aspect and this is
more about the presentation aspect where
it kind of like writes it out nicely and
uh boxes in the correct answer at the
bottom and so what's incredible about
this is we get this like thinking
process of the model and this is what's
coming from the reinforcement learning
process this is what's bloating up the
length of the token sequences they're
doing thinking and they're trying
different ways this is what's giving you
higher accuracy in problem
solving and this is where we are seeing
these aha moments and these different
strategies and these um ideas for how
you can make sure that you're getting
the correct
answer the last point I wanted to make
is some people are a little bit nervous
about putting you know very sensitive
data into chat.com because this is a
Chinese company so people don't um
people are a little bit careful and Cy
with that a little bit um deep seek R1
is a model that was released by this
company so this is an open source model
or open weights model it is available
for anyone to download and use you will
not be able to like run it in its full
um sort of the full model in full
Precision you won't run that on a
MacBook but uh or like a local device
because this is a fairly large model but
many companies are hosting the full
largest model one of those companies
that I like to use is called
together. so when you go to together.
you sign up and you go to playgrounds
you can can select here in the chat deep
seek R1 and there's many different kinds
of other models that you can select here
these are all state-of-the-art models so
this is kind of similar to the hugging
face inference playground that we've
been playing with so far but together. a
will usually host all the
state-of-the-art models so select DT
car1 um you can try to ignore a lot of
these I think the default settings will
often be okay and we can put in this and
because the model was released by Deep
seek what you're getting here should be
basically equivalent to what you're
getting here now because of the
randomness in the sampling we're going
to get something slightly different uh
but in principle this should be uh
identical in terms of the power of the
model and you should be able to see the
same things quantitatively and
qualitatively uh but uh this model is
coming from kind of a an American
company so that's deep seek and that's
the what's called a reasoning
model now when I go back to chat uh let
me go to chat here okay so the models
that you're going to see in the drop
down here some of them like 01 03 mini
O3 mini High Etc they are talking about
uses Advanced reasoning now what this is
referring to uses Advanced reasoning is
it's referring to the fact that it was
trained by reinforcement learning with
techniques very similar to those of deep
C car1 per public statements of opening
ey employees uh so these are thinking
models trained with RL and these models
like GPT 4 or GPT 4 40 mini that you're
getting in the free tier you should
think of them as mostly sft models
supervised fine tuning models they don't
actually do this like thinking as as you
see in the RL models and even though
there's a little bit of reinforcement
learning involved with these models and
I'll go that into that in a second these
are mostly sft models I think you should
think about it that way so in the same
way as what we saw here we can pick one
of the thinking models like say 03 mini
high and these models by the way might
not be available to you unless you pay a
Chachi PT subscription of either $20 per
month or $200 per month for some of the
top models so we can pick a thinking
model and run now what's going to happen
here is it's going to say reasoning and
it's going to start to do stuff like
this and um what we're seeing here is
not exactly the stuff we're seeing here
so even though under the hood the model
produces these kinds of uh kind of
chains of thought opening ey chooses to
not show the exact chains of thought in
the web interface it shows little
summaries of that of those chains of
thought and open kind of does this I
think partly because uh they are worried
about what's called the distillation
risk that is that someone could come in
and actually try to imitate those
reasoning traces and recover a lot of
the reasoning performance by just
imitating the reasoning uh chains of
thought and so they kind of hide them
and they only show little summaries of
them so you're not getting exactly what
you would get in deep seek as with
respect to the reasoning itself and then
they write up the
solution so these are kind of like
equivalent even though we're not seeing
the full under the hood details now in
terms of the performance uh these models
and deep seek models are currently rly
on par I would say it's kind of hard to
tell because of the evaluations but if
you're paying $200 per month to open AI
some of these models I believe are
currently they basically still look
better uh but deep seek R1 for now is
still a very solid choice for a thinking
model that would be available to you um
sort of um either on this website or any
other website because the model is open
weights you can just download it so
that's thinking models so what is the
summary so far well we've talked about
reinforcement learning and the fact that
thinking emerges in the process of the
optimization on when we basically run RL
on many math uh and kind of code
problems that have verifiable Solutions
so there's like an answer three
Etc now these thinking models you can
access in for example deep seek or any
inference provider like together. a and
choosing deep seek over there these
thinking models are also available uh in
chpt under any of the 01 or O3
models but these GPT 4 R models Etc
they're not thinking models you should
think of them as mostly sft models now
if you are um if you have a prompt that
requires Advanced reasoning and so on
you should probably use some of the
thinking models or at least try them out
but empirically for a lot of my use when
you're asking a simpler question there's
like a knowledge based question or
something like that this might be
Overkill like there's no need to think
30 seconds about some factual question
so for that I will uh sometimes default
to just GPT 40 so empirically about 80
90% of my use is just gp4
and when I come across a very difficult
problem like in math and code Etc I will
reach for the thinking models but then I
have to wait a bit longer because
they're thinking um so you can access
these on chat on deep seek also I wanted
to point out that um AI studio.
go.com even though it looks really busy
really ugly because Google's just unable
to do this kind of stuff well it's like
what is happening but if you choose
model and you choose here Gemini 2.0
flash thinking experimental 01 21 if you
choose that one that's also a a kind of
early experiment experimental of a
thinking model by Google so we can go
here and we can give it the same problem
and click run and this is also a
thinking problem a thinking model that
will also do something
similar and comes out with the right
answer here so basically Gemini also
offers a thinking model anthropic
currently does not offer a thinking
model but basically this is kind of like
the frontier development of these llms I
think RL is kind of like this new
exciting stage but getting the details
right is difficult and that's why all
these models and thinking models are
currently experimental as of 2025 very
early 2025 um but this is kind of like
the frontier development of pushing the
performance on these very difficult
problems using reasoning that is
emerging in these optimizations one more
connection that I wanted to bring up is
that the discovery that reinforcement
learning is extremely powerful way of
learning is not new to the field of AI
and one place what we've already seen
this demonstrated is in the game of Go
and famously Deep Mind developed the
system alphago and you can watch a movie
about it um where the system is learning
to play the game of go against top human
players and um when we go to the paper
underlying alphago so in this paper when
we scroll
down we actually find a really
interesting
plot um that I think uh is kind of
familiar uh to us and we're kind of like
we discovering in the more open domain
of arbitrary problem solving instead of
on the closed specific domain of the
game of Go but basically what they saw
and we're going to see this in llms as
well as this becomes more mature is this
is the ELO rating of playing game of Go
and this is leas dull an extremely
strong human player and here what they
are comparing is the strength of a model
learned trained by supervised learning
and a model trained by reinforcement
learning so the supervised learning
model is imitating human expert players
so if you just get a huge amount of
games played by expert players in the
game of Go and you try to imitate them
you are going to get better but then you
top out and you never quite get better
than some of the top top top players of
in the game of Go like LEL so you're
never going to reach there because
you're just imitating human players you
can't fundamentally go beyond a human
player if you're just imitating human
players but in a process of
reinforcement learning is significantly
more powerful in reinforcement learning
for a game of Go it means that the
system is playing moves that empirically
and statistically lead to win to winning
the game and so alphago is a system
where it kind of plays against it itself
and it's using reinforcement learning to
create
rollouts so it's the exact same diagram
here but there's no prompt it's just uh
because there's no prompt it's just a
fixed game of Go but it's trying out
lots of solutions it's trying out lots
of plays and then the games that lead to
a win instead of a specific answer are
reinforced they're they're made stronger
and so um the system is learning
basically the sequences of actions that
empirically and statistically lead to
winning the game and reinforcement
learning is not going to be constrained
by human performance and reinforcement
learning can do significantly better and
overcome even the top players like Lisa
Dole and so uh probably they could have
run this longer and they just chose to
crop it at some point because this costs
money but this is very powerful
demonstration of reinforcement learning
and we're only starting to kind of see
hints of this diagram in larger language
models for reasoning problems so we're
not going to get too far by just
imitating experts we need to go beyond
that set up these like little game
environments and get let let the system
discover reasoning traces or like ways
of solving problems uh that are unique
and that uh just basically work
well now on this aspect of uniqueness
notice that when you're doing
reinforcement learning nothing prevents
you from veering off the distribution of
how humans are playing the game and so
when we go back to uh this alphao search
here one of the suggested modifications
is called move 37 and move 37 in alphao
is referring to a specific point in time
where alphago basically played a move
that uh no human expert would play uh so
the probability of this move uh to be
played by a human player was evaluated
to be about 1 in 10th ,000 so it's a
very rare move but in retrospect it was
a brilliant move so alphago in the
process of reinforcement learning
discovered kind of like a strategy of
playing that was unknown to humans and
but is in retrospect uh brilliant I
recommend this YouTube video um leis do
versus alphao move 37 reactions and
Analysis and this is kind of what it
looked like when alphao played this
move
value that's a very that's a very
surprising move I thought I thought it
was I thought it was a
mistake when I see this move anyway so
basically people are kind of freaking
out because it's a it's a move that a
human would not play that alphago played
because in its training uh this move
seemed to be a good idea it just happens
not to be a kind of thing that a humans
would would do and so that is again the
power of reinforcement learning and in
principle we can actually see the
equivalence of that if we continue
scaling this Paradigm in language models
and what that looks like is kind of
unknown so so um what does it mean to
solve problems in such a way that uh
even humans would not be able to get how
can you be better at reasoning or
thinking than humans how can you go
beyond just uh a thinking human like
maybe it means discovering analogies
that humans would not be able to uh
create or maybe it's like a new thinking
strategy it's kind of hard to think
through uh maybe it's a holy new
language that actually is not even
English maybe it discovers its own
language that is a lot better at
thinking um because the model is
unconstrained to even like stick with
English uh so maybe it takes a different
language to think in or it discovers its
own language so in principle the
behavior of the system is a lot less
defined it is open to do whatever works
and it is open to also slowly Drift from
the distribution of its training data
which is English but all of that can
only be done if we have a very large
diverse set of problems in which the
these strategy can be refined and
perfected and so that is a lot of the
frontier LM research that's going on
right now is trying to kind of create
those kinds of prompt distributions that
are large and diverse these are all kind
of like game environments in which the
llms can practice their thinking and uh
it's kind of like writing you know these
practice problems we have to create
practice problems for all of domains of
knowledge and if we have practice
problems and tons of them the models
will be able to reinforcement learning
reinforcement learn on them and kind of
uh create these kinds of uh diagrams but
in the domain of open thinking instead
of a closed domain like game of Go
there's one more section within
reinforcement learning that I wanted to
cover and that is that of learning in
unverifiable domains so so far all of
the problems that we've looked at are in
what's called verifiable domains that is
any candidate solution we can score very
easily against a concrete answer so for
example answer is three and we can very
easily score these Solutions against the
answer of three
either we require the models to like box
in their answers and then we just check
for equality of whatever is in the box
with the answer or you can also use uh
kind of what's called an llm judge so
the llm judge looks at a solution and it
gets the answer and just basically
scores the solution for whether it's
consistent with the answer or not and
llms uh empirically are good enough at
the current capability that they can do
this fairly reliably so we can apply
those kinds of techniques as well in any
case we have a concrete answer and we're
just checking Solutions again against it
and we can do this automatically with no
kind of humans in the loop the problem
is that we can't apply the strategy in
what's called unverifiable domains so
usually these are for example creative
writing tasks like write a joke about
Pelicans or write a poem or summarize a
paragraph or something like that in
these kinds of domains it becomes harder
to score our different solutions to this
problem so for example writing a joke
about Pelicans we can generate lots of
different uh jokes of course that's fine
for example we can go to chbt and we can
get it to uh generate a joke about
Pelicans uh so much stuff in their beaks
because they don't bellan in
backpacks what
okay we can uh we can try something else
why don't Pelicans ever pay for their
drinks because they always B it to
someone else haha okay so these models
are not obviously not very good at humor
actually I think it's pretty fascinating
because I think humor is secretly very
difficult and the model have the
capability I think anyway in any case
you could imagine creating lots of jokes
the problem that we are facing is how do
we score them now in principle we could
of course get a human to look at all
these jokes just like I did right now
the problem with that is if you are
doing reinforcement learning you're
going to be doing many thousands of
updates and for each update you want to
be looking at say thousands of prompts
and for each prompt you want to be
potentially looking at looking at
hundred or thousands of different kinds
of generations and so there's just like
way too many of these to look at and so
um in principle you could have a human
inspect all of them and score them and
decide that okay maybe this one is funny
and uh maybe this one is funny and this
one is funny and we could train on them
to get the model to become slightly
better at jokes um in the context of
pelicans at least um the problem is that
it's just like way too much human time
this is an unscalable strategy we need
some kind of an automatic strategy for
doing this and one sort of solution to
this was proposed in this paper
uh that introduced what's called
reinforcement learning from Human
feedback and so this was a paper from
open at the time and many of these
people are now um co-founders in
anthropic um and this kind of proposed a
approach for uh basically doing
reinforcement learning in unverifiable
domains so let's take a look at how that
works so this is the cartoon diagram of
the core ideas involved so as I
mentioned the native approach is if we
just set Infinity human time we could
just run RL in these domains just fine
so for example we can run RL as usual if
I have Infinity humans I would I just
want to do and these are just cartoon
numbers I want to do 1,000 updates where
each update will be on 1,000 prompts and
in for each prompt we're going to have
1,000 roll outs that we're scoring so we
can run RL with this kind of a setup the
problem is in the process of doing this
I will need to run one I will need to
ask a human to evaluate a joke a total
of 1 billion times and so that's a lot
of people looking at really terrible
jokes so we don't want to do that so
instead we want to take the arlef
approach so um in our Rel of approach we
are kind of like the the core trick is
that of indirection so we're going to
involve humans just a little bit and the
way we cheat is that we basically train
a whole separate neural network that we
call a reward model and this neural
network will kind of like imitate human
scores so we're going to ask humans to
score um roll
we're going to then imitate human scores
using a neural network and this neural
network will become a kind of simulator
of human
preferences and now that we have a
neural network simulator we can do RL
against it so instead of asking a real
human we're asking a simulated human for
their score of a joke as an example and
so once we have a simulator we're often
racist because we can query it as many
times as we want to and it's all whole
automatic process and we can now do
reinforcement learning with respect to
the simulator and the simulator as you
might expect is not going to be a
perfect human but if it's at least
statistically similar to human judgment
then you might expect that this will do
something and in practice indeed uh it
does so once we have a simulator we can
do RL and everything works great so let
me show you a cartoon diagram a little
bit of what this process looks like
although the details are not 100 like
super important it's just a core idea of
how this works so here I have a cartoon
diagram of a hypothetical example of
what training the reward model would
look like so we have a prompt like write
a joke about picans and then here we
have five separate roll outs so these
are all five different jokes just like
this one now the first thing we're going
to do is we are going to ask a human to
uh order these jokes from the best to
worst so this is uh so here this human
thought that this joke is the best the
funniest so number one joke this is
number two joke number three joke four
and five so this is the worst joke
we're asking humans to order instead of
give scores directly because it's a bit
of an easier task it's easier for a
human to give an ordering than to give
precise scores now that is now the
supervision for the model so the human
has ordered them and that is kind of
like their contribution to the training
process but now separately what we're
going to do is we're going to ask a
reward model uh about its scoring of
these jokes now the reward model is a
whole separate neural network completely
separate neural net um and it's also
probably a transform
uh but it's not a language model in the
sense that it generates diverse language
Etc it's just a scoring model so the
reward model will take as an input The
Prompt number one and number two a
candidate joke so um those are the two
inputs that go into the reward model so
here for example the reward model would
be taken this prompt and this joke now
the output of a reward model is a single
number and this number is thought of as
a score and it can range for example
from Z to one so zero would be the worst
score and one would be the best score so
here are some examples of what a
hypothetical reward model at some stage
in the training process would give uh s
scoring to these jokes so 0.1 is a very
low score 08 is a really high score and
so on and so now um we compare the
scores given by the reward model with uh
the ordering given by the human and
there's a precise mathematical way to
actually calculate this uh basically set
up a loss function and calculate a kind
of like a correspondence here and uh
update a model based on it but I just
want to give you the intuition which is
that as an example here for this second
joke the the human thought that it was
the funniest and the model kind of
agreed right 08 is a relatively high
score but this score should have been
even higher right so after an update we
would expect that maybe this score
should have been will actually grow
after an update of the network to be
like say 081 or
something um for this one here they
actually are in a massive disagreement
because the human thought that this was
number two but here the the score is
only 0.1 and so this score needs to be
much higher so after an update on top of
this um kind of a supervision this might
grow a lot more like maybe it's 0.15 or
something like
that um and then here the human thought
that this one was the worst joke but
here the model actually gave it a fairly
High number so you might expect that
after the update uh this would come down
to maybe 3 3.5 or something like that so
basically we're doing what we did before
we're slightly nudging the predictions
from the models using a neural network
training
process and we're trying to make the
reward model scores be consistent with
human
ordering and so um as we update the
reward model on human data it becomes
better and better simulator of the
scores and orders uh that humans provide
and then becomes kind of like the the
neural the simulator of human
preferences which we can then do RL
against but critically we're not asking
humans one billion times to look at a
joke we're maybe looking at th000
prompts and five roll outs each so maybe
5,000 jokes that humans have to look at
in total and they just give the ordering
and then we're training the model to be
consistent with that ordering and I'm
skipping over the mathematical details
but I just want you to understand a high
level idea that uh this reward model is
do is basically giving us this scour and
we have a way of training it to be
consistent with human orderings
and that's how rhf works okay so that is
the rough idea we basically train
simulators of humans and RL with respect
to those
simulators now I want to talk about
first the upside of reinforcement
learning from Human
feedback the first thing is that this
allows us to run reinforcement learning
which we know is incredibly powerful
kind of set of techniques and it allows
us to do it in arbitrary domains and
including the ones that are unverifiable
so things like summarization and poem
writing joke writing or any other
creative writing really uh in domains
outside of math and code
Etc now empirically what we see when we
actually apply rhf is that this is a way
to improve the performance of the model
and uh I have a top answer for why that
might be but I don't actually know that
it is like super well established on
like why this is you can empirically
observe that when you do rhf correctly
the models you get are just like a
little bit better um but as to why is I
think like not as clear so here's my
best guess my best guess is that this is
possibly mostly due to the discriminator
generator
Gap what that means is that in many
cases it is significantly easier to
discriminate than to generate for humans
so in particular an example of this is
um in when we do supervised fine-tuning
right
sft we're asking humans to generate the
ideal assistant response and in many
cases here um as I've shown it uh the
ideal response is very simple to write
but in many cases might not be so for
example in summarization or poem writing
or joke writing like how are you as a
human assist as a human labeler um
supposed to give the ideal response in
these cases it requires creative human
writing to do that and so rhf kind of
sidesteps this because we get um we get
to ask people a significantly easier
question as a data labelers they're not
asked to write poems directly they're
just given five poems from the model and
they're just asked to order them and so
that's just a much easier task for a
human labeler to do and so what I think
this allows you to do basically is it um
it kind of like allows a lot more higher
accuracy data because we're not asking
people to do the generation task which
can be extremely difficult like we're
not asking them to do creative writing
we're just trying to get them to
distinguish between creative writings
and uh find the ones that are best and
that is the signal that humans are
providing just the ordering and that is
their input into the system and then the
system in rhf just discovers the kinds
of responses that would be graded well
by humans and so that step of
indirection allows the models to become
a bit better so that is the upside of
our LF it allows us to run RL it
empirically results in better models and
it allows uh people to contribute their
supervision uh even without having to do
extremely difficult tasks um in the case
of writing ideal responses unfortunately
our HF also comes with significant
downsides and so um the main one is that
basically we are doing reinforcement
learning not with respect to humans and
actual human judgment but with respect
to a lossy simulation of humans right
and this lossy simulation could be
misleading because it's just a it's just
a simulation right it's just a language
model that's kind of outputting scores
and it might not perfectly reflect the
opinion of an actual human with an
actual brain in all the possible
different cases so that's number one
which is actually something even more
subtle and devious going on that uh
really
dramatically holds back our LF as a
technique that we can really scale to
significantly um kind of Smart Systems
and that is that reinforcement learning
is extremely good at discovering a way
to game the model to game the simulation
so this reward model that we're
constructing here that gives the course
these models are Transformers these
Transformers are massive neurals they
have billions of parameters and they
imitate humans but they do so in a kind
of like a simulation way now the problem
is that these are massive complicated
systems right there's a billion
parameters here that are outputting a
single
score it turns out that there are ways
to gain these models you can find kinds
of inputs that were not part of their
training set and these inputs
inexplicably get very high scores but in
a fake way so very often what you find
if you run our lch for very long so for
example if we do 1,000 updates which is
like say a lot of updates you might
expect that your jokes are getting
better and that you're getting like real
bangers about Pelicans but that's not
EXA exactly what happens what happens is
that uh in the first few hundred steps
the jokes about Pelicans are probably
improving a little bit and then they
actually dramatically fall off the cliff
and you start to get extremely
nonsensical results like for example you
start to get um the top joke about
Pelicans starts to be the
and this makes no sense right like when
you look at it why should this be a top
joke but when you take the the and you
plug it into your reward model you'd
expect score of zero but actually the
reward model loves this as a joke it
will tell you that the the the theth is
a score of 1. Z this is a top joke and
this makes no sense right but it's
because these models are just
simulations of humans and they're
massive neural lots and you can find
inputs at the bottom that kind of like
get into the part of the input space
that kind of gives you nonsensical
results these examples are what's called
adversarial examples and I'm not going
to go into the topic too much but these
are adversarial inputs to the model they
are specific little inputs that kind of
go between the nooks and crannies of the
model and give nonsensical results at
the top now here's what you might
imagine doing you say okay the the the
is obviously not score of one um it's
obviously a low score so let's take the
the the the the let's add it to the data
set and give it an ordering that is
extremely bad like a score of five and
indeed your model will learn that the D
should have a very low score and it will
give it score of zero the problem is
that there will always be basically
infinite number of nonsensical
adversarial examples hiding in the model
if you iterate this process many times
and you keep adding nonsensical stuff to
your reward model and giving it very low
scores you can you'll never win the game
uh you can do this many many rounds and
reinforcement learning if you run it
long enough will always find a way to
gain the model it will discover
adversarial examples it will get get
really high scores uh with nonsensical
results and fundamentally this is
because our scoring function is a giant
neural nut and RL is extremely good at
finding just the ways to trick it uh so
long story short you always run rhf put
for maybe a few hundred updates the
model is getting better and then you
have to crop it and you are done you
can't run too much against this reward
model because the optimization will
start to game it and you basically crop
it and you call it and you ship it um
and uh you can improve the reward model
but you kind of like come across these
situations eventually at some point so
rhf basically what I usually say is that
RF is not RL and what I mean by that is
I mean RF is RL obviously but it's not
RL in the magical sense this is not RL
that you can run
indefinitely these kinds of problems
like where you are getting con correct
answer you cannot gain this as easily
you either got the correct answer or you
didn't and the scoring function is much
much simpler you're just looking at the
boxed area and seeing if the result is
correct so it's very difficult to gain
these functions but uh gaming a reward
model is possible now in these
verifiable domains you can run RL
indefinitely you could run for tens of
thousands hundreds of thousands of steps
and discover all kinds of really crazy
strategies that we might not even ever
think about of Performing really well
for all these problems in the game of Go
there's no way to to beat to basically
game uh the winning of a game or the
losing of a game we have a perfect
simulator we know all the different uh
where all the stones are placed and we
can calculate uh whether someone has won
or not there's no way to gain that and
so you can do RL indefinitely and you
can eventually be beat even leol but
with models like this which are gameable
you cannot repeat this process
indefinitely so I kind of see rhf as not
real RL because the reward function is
gameable so it's kind of more like in
the realm of like little fine-tuning
it's a little it's a little Improvement
but it's not something that is
fundamentally set up correctly where you
can insert more compute run for longer
and get much better and magical results
so it's it's uh it's not RL in that
sense it's not RL in the sense that it
lacks magic um it can find you in your
model and get a better performance and
indeed if we go back to chat GPT the GPT
40 model has gone through rhf because it
works well but it's just not RL in the
same sense rlf is like a little fine
tune that slightly improves your model
is maybe like the way I would think
about it okay so that's most of the
technical content that I wanted to cover
I took you through the three major
stages and paradigms of training these
models pre-training supervised fine
tuning and reinforcement learning and I
showed you that they Loosely correspond
to the process we already use for
teaching children and so in particular
we talked about pre-training being sort
of like the basic knowledge acquisition
of reading Exposition supervised fine
tuning being the process of looking at
lots and lots of worked examples and
imitating experts and practice problems
the only difference is that we now have
to effectively write textbooks for llms
and AIS across all the disciplines of
human knowledge and also in all the
cases where we actually would like them
to work like code and math and you know
basically all the other disciplines so
we're in the process of writing
textbooks for them refining all the
algorithms that I've presented on the
high level and then of course doing a
really really good job at the execution
of training these models at scale and
efficiently so in particular I didn't go
into too many details but these are
extremely large and complicated
distributed uh sort of
um jobs that have to run over tens of
thousands or even hundreds of thousands
of gpus and the engineering that goes
into this is really at the stateof the
art of what's possible with computers at
that scale so I didn't cover that aspect
too much
but um this is very kind of serious and
they were underlying all these very
simple algorithms
ultimately now I also talked about sort
of like the theory of mind a little bit
of these models and the thing I want you
to take away is that these models are
really good but they're extremely useful
as tools for your work you shouldn't uh
sort of trust them fully and I showed
you some examples of that even though we
have mitigations for hallucinations the
models are not perfect and they will
hallucinate still it's gotten better
over time and it will continue to get
better but they can
hallucinate in other words in in
addition to that I covered kind of like
what I call the Swiss cheese uh sort of
model of llm capabilities that you
should have in your mind the models are
incredibly good across so many different
disciplines but then fail randomly
almost in some unique cases so for
example what is bigger 9.11 or 9.9 like
the model doesn't know but
simultaneously it can turn around and
solve Olympiad questions and so this is
a hole in the Swiss cheese and there are
many of them and you don't want to trip
over them so don't um treat these models
as infallible models check their work
use them as tools use them for
inspiration use them for the first draft
but uh work with them as tools and be
ultimately respons responsible for the
you know product of your
work and that's roughly what I wanted to
talk about this is how they're trained
and this is what they are let's now turn
to what are some of the future
capabilities of these models uh probably
what's coming down the pipe and also
where can you find these models I have a
few blow points on some of the things
that you can expect coming down the pipe
the first thing you'll notice is that
the models will very rapidly become
multimodal everything I talked about
above concerned text but very soon we'll
have llms that can not just handle text
but they can also operate natively and
very easily over audio so they can hear
and speak and also images so they can
see and paint and we're already seeing
the beginnings of all of this uh but
this will be all done natively inside
inside the language model and this will
enable kind of like natural
conversations and roughly speaking the
reason that this is actually no
different from everything we've covered
above is that as a baseline you can
tokenize audio and images and apply the
exact same approaches of everything that
we've talked about above so it's not a
fundamental change it's just uh it's
just a to we have to add some tokens so
as an example for tokenizing audio we
can look at slices of the spectrogram of
the audio signal and we can tokenize
that and just add more tokens that
suddenly represent audio and just add
them into the context windows and train
on them just like above the same for
images we can use patches and we can
separately tokenize patches and then
what is an image an image is just a
sequence of tokens and this actually
kind of works and there's a lot of early
work in this direction and so we can
just create streams of tokens that are
representing audio images as well as
text and interpers them and handle them
all simultaneously in a single model so
that's one example of multimodality
uh second something that people are very
interested in
is currently most of the work is that
we're handing individual tasks to the
models on kind of like a silver platter
like please solve this task for me and
the model sort of like does this little
task but it's up to us to still sort of
like organize a coherent execution of
tasks to perform jobs and the models are
not yet at the capability required to do
this in a coherent error correcting way
over long periods of time so they're not
able to fully string together tasks to
perform these longer running jobs but
they're getting there and this is
improving uh over time but uh probably
what's going to happen here is we're
going to start to see what's called
agents which perform tasks over time and
you you supervise them and you watch
their work and they come up to once in a
while report progress and so on so we're
going to see more long running agents uh
tasks that don't just take you know a
few seconds of response but many tens of
seconds or even minutes or hours over
time uh but these uh models are not
infallible as we talked about above so
all of this will require supervision so
for example in factories people talk
about the human to robot ratio uh for
automation I think we're going to see
something similar in the digital space
where we are going to be talking about
human to agent ratios where humans
becomes a lot more supervisors of agent
tasks um in the digital
domain uh next um I think everything is
going to become a lot more pervasive and
invisible so it's kind of like
integrated into the tools and everywhere
um and in addition kind of like computer
using so right now these models aren't
able to take actions on your behalf but
I think this is a separate bullet point
um if you saw chpt launch the operator
then uh that's one early example of that
where you can actually hand off control
to the model to perform you know
keyboard and mouse actions on your
behalf so that's also something that
that I think is very interesting the
last point I have here is just a general
comment that there's still a lot of
research to potentially do in this
domain main one example of that uh is
something along the lines of test time
training so remember that everything
we've done above and that we talked
about has two major stages there's first
the training stage where we tune the
parameters of the model to perform the
tasks well once we get the parameters we
fix them and then we deploy the model
for inference from there the model is
fixed it doesn't change anymore it
doesn't learn from all the stuff that
it's doing a test time it's a fixed um
number of parameters and the only thing
that is changing is now the token inside
the context windows and so the only type
of learning or test time learning that
the model has access to is the in
context learning of its uh kind of like
uh dynamically adjustable context window
depending on like what it's doing at
test time so but I think this is still
different from humans who actually are
able to like actually learn uh depending
on what they're doing especially when
you sleep for example like your brain is
updating your parameters or something
like that right so there's no kind of
equivalent of that currently in these
models and tools so there's a lot of
like um more wonky ideas I think that
are to be explored still and uh in
particular I think this will be
necessary because the context window is
a finite and precious resource and
especially once we start to tackle very
long running multimodal tasks and we're
putting in videos and these token
windows will basically start to grow
extremely large like not thousands or
even hundreds of thousands but
significantly beyond that and the only
trick uh the only kind of trick we have
Avail to us right now is to make the
context Windows longer but I think that
that approach by itself will will not
will not scale to actual long running
tasks that are multimodal over time and
so I think new ideas are needed in some
of those disciplines um in some of those
kind of cases in the main where these
tasks are going to require very long
contexts so those are some examples of
some of the things you can um expect
coming down the pipe let's now turn to
where you can actually uh kind of keep
track of this progress and um you know
be up to date with the latest and grest
of what's happening in the field so I
would say the three resources that I
have consistently used to stay up to
date are number one El Marina uh so let
me show you El
Marina this is basically an llm leader
board and it ranks all the top models
and the ranking is based on human
comparisons so humans prompt these
models and they get to judge which one
gives a better answer they don't know
which model is which they're just
looking at which model is the better
answer and you can calculate a ranking
and then you get some results and so
what you can hear is what you can see
here is the different organizations like
Google Gemini for example that produce
these models when you click on any one
of these it takes you to the place where
that model is
hosted and then here we see Google is
currently on top with open AI right
behind here we see deep seek in position
number three now the reason this is a
big deal is the last column here you see
license deep seek is an MIT license
model it's open weights anyone can use
these weights uh anyone can download
them anyone can host their own version
of Deep seek and they can use it in what
whatever way they like and so it's not a
proprietary model that you don't have
access to it's it's basically an open
weight release and so this is kind of
unprecedented that a model this strong
was released with open weights so pretty
cool from the team next up we have a few
more models from Google and open Ai and
then when you continue to scroll down
you start to see some other Usual
Suspects so xai here anthropic with son
it uh here at number
14 and
um then
meta with llama over here so llama
similar to deep seek is an open weights
model and so uh but it's down here as
opposed to up here now I will say that
this leaderboard was really good for a
long time I do think that in the last
few months it's become a little bit
gamed um and I don't trust it as much as
I used to I think um just empirically I
feel like a lot of people for example
are using a Sonet from anthropic and
that it's a really good model so but
that's all the way down here um in
number 14 and conversely I think not as
many people are using Gemini but it's
racking really really high uh so I think
use this as a first pass uh but uh sort
of try out a few of the models for your
tasks and see which one performs better
the second thing that I would point to
is the uh AI news uh newsletter so AI
news is not very creatively named but it
is a very good newsletter produced by
swix and friends so thank you for
maintaining it
and it's been very helpful to me because
it is extremely comprehensive so if you
go to archives uh you see that it's
produced almost every other day and um
it is very comprehensive and some of it
is written by humans and curated by
humans but a lot of it is constructed
automatically with llms so you'll see
that these are very comprehensive and
you're probably not missing anything
major if you go through it of course
you're probably not going to go through
it because it's so long but I do think
that these summaries all the way up top
are quite good and I think have some
human oversight uh so this has been very
helpful to me and the last thing I would
point to is just X and Twitter uh a lot
of um AI happens on X and so I would
just follow people who you like and
trust and get all your latest and
greatest uh on X as well so those are
the major places that have worked for me
over time and finally a few words on
where you can find the models and where
can you use them so the first one I
would say is for any of the biggest
proprietary models you just have to go
to the website of that LM provider so
for example for open a that's uh chat
I believe actually works now uh so
that's for open
AI now for or you know for um for Gemini
I think it's gem. google.com or AI
Studio I think they have two for some
reason that I don't fly understand no
one does um for the open weights models
like deep SE CL Etc you have to go to
some kind of an inference provider of
LMS so my favorite one is together
together. a and I showed you that when
you go to the playground of together. a
then you can sort of pick lots of
different models and all of these are
open models of different types and you
can talk to them here as an
example um now if you'd like to use a
base model like um you know a base model
then this is where I think it's not as
common to find base models even on these
inference providers they are all
targeting assistants and chat and so I
think even here I can't I couldn't see
base models here so for base models I
usually go to hyperbolic because they
serve my llama 3.1 base and I love that
model and you can just talk to it here
so as far as I know this is this is a
good place for a base model and I wish
more people hosted base models because
they are useful and interesting to work
with in some cases finally you can also
take some of the models that are smaller
and you can run them locally and so for
example deep seek the biggest model
you're not going to be able to run
locally on your MacBook but there are
smaller versions of the deep seek model
that are what's called distilled and
then also you can run these models at
smaller Precision so not at the native
Precision of for example fp8 on deep
seek or you know bf16 llama but much
much lower than that um and don't worry
if you don't fully understand those
details but you can run smaller versions
that have been distilled and then at
even lower precision and then you can
fit them on your uh computer and so you
can actually run pretty okay models on
your laptop and my favorite I think
place I go to usually is LM studio uh
which is basically an app you can get
and I think it kind of actually looks
really ugly and it's I don't like that
it shows you all these models that are
basically not that useful like everyone
just wants to run deep seek so I don't
know why they give you these 500
different types of models they're really
complicated to search for and you have
to choose different distillations and
different uh precisions and it's all
really confusing but once you actually
understand how it works and that's a
whole separate video then you can
actually load up a model like here I
loaded up a llama 3 uh2 instruct 1
billion and um you can just talk to it
so I ask for Pelican jokes and I can ask
for another one and it gives me another
one Etc all of this that happens here is
locally on your computer so we're not
actually going to anywhere anyone else
this is running on the GPU on the
MacBook Pro so that's very nice and you
can then eject the model when you're
done and that frees up the ram so LM
studio is probably like my favorite one
even though I don't I think it's got a
lot of uiux issues and it's really
geared towards uh professionals almost
uh but if you watch some videos on
YouTube I think you can figure out how
to how to use this
interface uh so those are a few words on
where to find them so let me now loop
back around to where we started the
question was when we go to chashi
pta.com and we enter some kind of a
query and we hit go what exactly is
happening here what are we seeing what
are we talking to how does this work and
I hope that this video gave you some
appreciation for some of the under the
hood details of how these models are
trained and what this is that is coming
back so in particular we now know that
your query is taken and is first chopped
up into tokens so we go to to tick
tokenizer and here where is the place in
the in the um sort of format that is for
the user query we basically put in our
query right there so our query goes into
what we discussed here is the
conversation protocol format which is
this way that we maintain conversation
objects so this gets inserted there and
then this whole thing ends up being just
a token sequence a onedimensional token
sequence under the hood so Chachi PT saw
this token sequence and then when we hit
go it basically continues appending
tokens into this list it continues the
sequence it acts like a token
autocomplete so in particular it gave us
this response so we can basically just
put it here and we see the tokens that
it continued uh these are the tokens
that it continued with
roughly now the question
becomes okay why are these the tokens
that the model responded with what are
these tokens where are they coming from
uh what are we talking to and how do we
program this system and so that's where
we shifted gears and we talked about the
under thehood pieces of it so the first
stage of this process and there are
three stages is the pre-training stage
which fundamentally has to do with just
knowledge acquisition from the internet
into the parameters of this neural
network and so the neural net
internalizes a lot of Knowledge from the
internet but where the personality
really comes in is in the process of
supervised fine-tuning here and so what
what happens here is that basically the
a company like openai will curate a
large data set of conversations like say
1 million conversation across very
diverse topics and there will be
conversations between a human and an
assistant and even though there's a lot
of synthetic data generation used
throughout this entire process and a lot
of llm help and so on fundamentally this
is a human data curation task with lots
of humans involved and in particular
these humans are data labelers hired by
open AI who are given labeling
instructions that they learn and they
task is to create ideal assistant
responses for any arbitrary prompts so
they are teaching the neural network by
example how to respond to
prompts so what is the way to think
about what came back here like what is
this well I think the right way to think
about it is that this is the neural
network simulation of a data labeler at
openai so it's as if I gave this query
to a data Li open and this data labeler
first reads all of the labeling
instructions from open Ai and then
spends 2 hours writing up the ideal
assistant response to this query and uh
giving it to me now we're not actually
doing that right because we didn't wait
two hours so what we're getting here is
a neural network simulation of that
process and we have to keep in mind that
these neural networks don't function
like human brains do they are different
what's easy or hard for them is
different from what's easy or hard for
humans and so we really are just getting
a simulation so here I shown you this is
a token stream and this is fundamentally
the neural network with a bunch of
activations and neurons in between this
is a fixed mathematical expression that
mixes inputs from tokens with parameters
of the model and they get mixed up and
get you the next token in a sequence but
this is a finite amount of compute that
happens for every single token and so
this is some kind of a lossy simulation
of a human that is kind of like
restricted in this way and so whatever
the humans
write the language model is kind of
imitating on this token level with only
this this specific computation for every
single token and
sequence we also saw that as a result of
this and the cognitive differences the
models will suffer in a variety of ways
and uh you have to be very careful with
their use so for example we saw that
they will suffer from hallucinations and
they also we have the sense of a Swiss
model of the LM capabilities where
basically there's like holes in the
cheese sometimes the models will just
arbitrarily like do something dumb uh so
even though they're doing lots of
magical stuff sometimes they just can't
so maybe you're not giving them enough
tokens to think and maybe they're going
to just make stuff up because they're
mental arithmetic breaks uh maybe they
are suddenly unable to count number of
letters um or maybe they're unable to
tell you that 911 9.11 is smaller than
9.9 and it looks kind of dumb and so so
it's a Swiss cheese capability and we
have to be careful with that and we saw
the reasons for
that but fundamentally this is how we
think of what came back it's again a
simulation of this neural network of a
human data labeler following the
labeling instructions at open a so
that's what we're getting back now I do
think that the uh things change a little
bit when you actually go and reach for
one of the thinking models like o03 mini
and the reason for that is that GPT
40 basically doesn't do reinforcement
learning it does do rhf but I've told
you that rhf is not RL there's no
there's no uh time for magic in there
it's just a little bit of a fine-tuning
is the way to look at it but these
thinking models they do use RL so they
go through this third state stage of
perfecting their thinking process and
discovering new thinking strategies and
uh
solutions to problem solving that look a
little bit like your internal monologue
in your head and they practice that on a
large collection of practice problems
that companies like openi create and
curate and um then make available to the
LMS so when I come here and I talked to
a thinking model and I put in this
question what we're seeing here is not
anymore just the straightforward
simulation of a human data labeler like
this is actually kind of new unique and
interesting um and of course open is not
showing us the under thehood thinking
and the chains of thought that are
underlying the reasoning here but we
know that such a thing exists and this
is a summary of it and what we're
getting here is actually not just an
imitation of a human data labeler it's
actually something that is kind of new
and interesting and exciting in the
sense that it is a function of thinking
that was emergent in a simulation it's
not just imitating human data labeler it
comes from this reinforcement learning
process and so here we're of course not
giving it a chance to shine because this
is not a mathematical or a reasoning
problem this is just some kind of a sort
of creative writing problem roughly
speaking and I think it's um it's a a
question an open question as to whether
the thinking strategies that are
developed inside verifiable domains
transfer and are generalizable to other
domains that are unverifiable such as
create writing the extent to which that
transfer happens is unknown in the field
I would say so we're not sure if we are
able to do RL on everything that is very
verifiable and see the benefits of that
on things that are unverifiable like
this prompt so that's an open question
the other thing that's interesting is
that this reinforcement learning here is
still like way too new primordial and
nent so we're just seeing like the
beginnings of the hints of greatness uh
in the reasoning problems we're seeing
something that is in principle capable
of something like the equivalent of move
37 but not in the game of Go but in open
domain thinking and problem solving in
principle this Paradigm is capable of
doing something really cool new and
exciting something even that no human
has thought of before in principle these
models are capable of analogies no human
has had so I think it's incredibly
exciting that these models exist but
again it's very early and these are
primordial models for now um and they
will mostly shine in domains that are
verifiable like math en code Etc so very
interesting to play with and think about
and
use and then that's roughly it um um I
would say those are the broad Strokes of
what's available right now I will say
that overall it is an extremely exciting
time to be in the
field personally I use these models all
the time daily uh tens or hundreds of
times because they dramatically
accelerate my work I think a lot of
people see the same thing I think we're
going to see a huge amount of wealth
creation as a result of these models be
aware of some of their shortcomings even
with RL models they're going to suffer
from some of these use it as a tool in a
toolbox don't trust it fully because
they will randomly do dumb things they
will randomly hallucinate they will
randomly skip over some mental
arithmetic and not get it right um they
randomly can't count or something like
that so use them as tools in the toolbox
check their work and own the product of
your work but use them for inspiration
for first draft uh ask them questions
but always check and verify and you will
be very successful in your work if you
do so uh so I hope this video was useful
and interesting to you I hope you had it
fun and uh it's already like very long
so I apologize for that but I hope it
was useful and yeah I will see you later